<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A soul-searching catechism wherein is opened and explained not onely the six fundamental points set down Heb. 6. I. but also many other questions of highest concernment in Christian religion : wherein is strong meat for them that are grown and milk for babes, in a very short catechism at the end, exceeding needful for all families in these ignorant and unsetled times / written by Christopher Blackwood.</title>
            <author>Blackwood, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08401588</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08401588</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28310)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1247:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A soul-searching catechism wherein is opened and explained not onely the six fundamental points set down Heb. 6. I. but also many other questions of highest concernment in Christian religion : wherein is strong meat for them that are grown and milk for babes, in a very short catechism at the end, exceeding needful for all families in these ignorant and unsetled times / written by Christopher Blackwood.</title>
                  <author>Blackwood, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with addition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews IV, 1 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Catechisms.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41271:1"/>
            <p>A Soul-ſearching CATECHISM, Wherein is opened and explained, Not onely the Six Fundamental Points ſet down <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.</p>
            <p>But alſo many other Queſtions of higheſt concernment in Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſtrong meat for thoſe that are grown, and milk for babes, in a very ſhort Catechiſm at the end, exceeding needful for all Families, in theſe ignorant and unſetled Times.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Christopher Blackwood,</hi> a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition, with Addition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.21.</hi>
               </bibl> Prove all things: hold faſt that which is good.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 1.12.</hi>
               </bibl> Hold faſt the form of ſound words which thou haſt heard.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 1.3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl> It ſeemed good to me to write, that thou mightſt know the certainty of thoſe things wherein thou haſt been inſtructed.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41271:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41271:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O preach unto people, and not to catechize them, I take to be a building without laying a foundation. Hence the Apoſtle firſt laid the foundation of the ſix Principles, <hi>Heb. 6.1, 2. Not laying again the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Repentance from dead works, of Faith towards God, of the doctrine of Baptiſms, and Laying on of hands, of the Reſurrection of the dead, and of the eternal Judgment.</hi> After which Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, I have propoſed unto thee the Reader a <hi>form</hi> (I truſt) <hi>of ſound words,</hi> wherein thou mayſt inſtruct thy Family. That thou mayſt do it the better to thine own comfort, and their edification, take theſe Directions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Cauſe thy children and ſervants to commit to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory the ſhort Catechiſm which is at the end of the Book.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Every time thou doſt catechize in thy Family, which I would have thee to do once every week at leaſt, read and explain to them one or two of the larger queſtions; and do them and me that favour, as to turn to the places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which, for brevity ſake, I could not write down; and read them unto them, and ſhew them how the alleadged Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures prove the point in hand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If thy ſervants and children be more towardly, or more ingeniouſly bred, or more quick witted, let them learn without book the larger Catechiſm: but if they be more ſlow
<pb facs="tcp:41271:3"/> and uncapable, let them onely learn the ſecond; and oft read and expound to them the former, remembring that narrow-mouth'd veſſels can receive liquors poured into them onely by degrees.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Pray for a bleſsing upon the Inſtruction, without which, thy pains will not be effectual.</p>
            <p>If thou art different in judgement from me in ſome one Point propoſed, yet let not that hinder thee from informing others in the reſt of the Points wherein we are agreed. If upon pretence of errour in ſome one Point, thou ſhalt conceal the whole from thy Family, for fear they ſhould be drawn away with error; take heed that the things herein contained, which thou acknowledgeſt ſound, be not a witneſs againſt thy miſ-guided Zeal (mingled with Cruelty) in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as thou liveſt in times wherein many, for want of ſound Principles laid at firſt, go a whoring from God after ſundry, dangerous, and deſtructive Errours; let it be thy care to train up thine in their youth, in the way of Truth, that they may not depart from it when they are old.</p>
            <p>So heartily deſiring that the Spirit of Grace would make theſe Inſtructions home to thy heart, which I preſent to thy eye and ear, I take my leave, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine affectionate friend, in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Chriſtopher Blackwood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41271:3"/>
            <head>A Short Catechiſm, As at all times uſeful, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in theſe unſetled times.</head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat grounds have you to prove there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By his Creation of Heaven and Earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the confeſſion of all Nations, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo barbarous, that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a God, though moſt men are ignorant of the true God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the order of cauſes: of every effect there muſt needs be a cauſe, till we come to the firſt univerſal cauſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the Conſciences of wicked men; who having ſinned, are afraid of being puniſh'd by ſome ſupream Judg, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. <hi>John</hi> 8.9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the Providence of God, ſeen 1. in diſpenſing puniſhments to the ungodly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. and rewards to the righteous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58.11. 2. In making proviſion for all Creatures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10 4. throughout. 3. In the fitting one thing for another, as the eye and colour, and light and the air, a thin body, through which colours
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41271:4"/> are ſent to the eye. 4 The actions of unreaſonable creatures above their ability, as the Ant, Spider, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ordering of contraries to unity.</p>
            <p n="6">6. There is a Devil that ſuggeſts evil, therefore there is a God that ſuggeſts good motions; and though he be not ſeen, no more is the winde, or ſoul of man.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are we to conſider in God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. His nature; 2. his kingdom; 3. his worke.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are we to conſider concerning his nature?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Unity of the Eſſence, together with the Trinity of Subſiſtence; how that the Godhead ſubſiſteth in the being of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; yet they are not three Gods, but one, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Can we underſtand God in his eſſence, as he is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No further then he hath revealed himſelf; yet we know him, by conſidering all the perfections that are in any creature; as wiſdom, juſtice, bounty, holineſs, mercy, ſtrength; and aſcribing them all to him. 2. By removing all the imperfections that are in any creature from him; ſo we ſay God cannot die, nor ſuffer, nor ſin.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How prove you the Father to be God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 Cor. 8.6. <hi>There is to us but one God, the Father.</hi> Gal. 1.1. <hi>God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.2. <hi>Through the foreknowledg of God the Father.</hi> Jude 1.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How prove you the Son to be God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the Scripture calls him <hi>God over all, bleſſed for ever,</hi> Rom. 9.5. Phil. 2.6. <hi>He thought it no robbery to be equal with God.</hi> Beſides, none but God could make the world: now Chriſt made the world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.15, 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. Alſo the Saints have pray'd unto him, as well as unto the Father; <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Steven</hi> cry'd <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit.</hi> Heb. 1.6. <hi>When he bringeth his firſt begotten into the world, he ſaith, Let all the Angels of God worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How prove you the Holy Ghoſt to be God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe we are baptized into his name, and received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant by him, as well as by the Father and Son; and he promiſes pardon of ſin, and eternal life, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. Again,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41271:4"/> the Scripture calls him God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3, 4. <hi>Why hath Satan fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy heart to lye to the Holy Ghoſt? thou haſt not lyed unto men, but unto God.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.16. <hi>Know ye not that ye are the temple of God?</hi> compared with 1 Cor. 6.19. <hi>Know ye not that your body is the temple of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> he that in one place is called the Holy Ghoſt, in the other is called God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 95.7. in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> it's ſaid, <hi>They tempted the Holy ghoſt:</hi> in the <hi>Pſalmes, They tempted God. Acts</hi> 28.25. compared with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.8. in the <hi>Acts</hi> its ſaid, <hi>The Holy ghoſt ſpake to Iſaiah:</hi> but in <hi>Iſa.</hi> its ſaid, <hi>the Lord ſpake unto him,</hi> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord <hi>whoſe train filled the temple.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are not our own but the Holy ghoſts:</hi> therefore he hath abſolute power over us. Now God alone hath abſolute power over us. Yea, he bids us <hi>glorifie God with our bodies.</hi> Now what God means he, ſave the Holy ghoſt, whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies he call'd his temple?</p>
            <p>Further, his Godhead appears, becauſe he <hi>ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10, 11. As the minde of a man knows all the things of man, becauſe it is in him; ſo doth the Spirit of God know the things of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. <hi>You do always reſiſt the Holy ghoſt, as your fathers did.</hi> Now whom did their fathers reſiſt in the Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but God?</p>
            <p>Beſides, his Godhead was ſeen, in inabling perſons to ſpeak with tongues of all ſorts, without any teaching of them by man, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether is the Holy ghoſt only a motion, action, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, whereby God works effectually in the hearts of the elect; or whether is he an underſtanding, willing, working ſubſtance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is an underſtanding, willing, working ſubſtance, becauſe he is ſaid to be blaſphemed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.30, 31. Now an action cannot properly be ſaid to be blaſphemed, but a perſon. Againe, the holy Spirit is ſaid to be a Comforter, and to teſtifie of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 15.26. <hi>When the Comforter is come, whom I will ſend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, he ſhall teſtifie of me:</hi> therefore a perſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. The Holy ghoſt bad <hi>ſeparate Paul and Barnabas for the work;</hi> yea, he ſets overſeers over Gods flock, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.18. <hi>It ſeems good to the Holy ghoſt and to us.</hi> If it ſeem'd good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41271:5"/> to him, then he is a perſon indued with underſtanding <hi>Acts</hi> 16.6. The Holy ghoſt forbad the Apoſtles to go to <hi>Phrygia</hi> and <hi>Bithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and bad them go to <hi>Macedonia;</hi> becauſe he commands and forbids, he is a Subſtance. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. <hi>the love of God</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy ghoſt.</hi> The Apoſtle herein puts a full difference betwixt the gifts of God, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt. Beſides, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. He diſtributes gifts to every one <hi>even as he pleaſeth:</hi> therefore he is a perſon or ſubſtance; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.16.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Wether is the holy ghoſt equal with the Father and Son?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and communion of the holy ghoſt, be with you.</hi> The Apoſtle joyns the holy ghoſt with the other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in prayer. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>theſe three are one: Pſal.</hi> 33.6. all the hoſt of Heaven was made by the Spirit, as well as by Father and Son, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>The Spirit of God moved upon the waters.</hi> The holy ghoſt alſo takes us into Covenant, and in his name are we baptized, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. which were unlawful, were he not God equal with the Father. The holy ghoſt makes covenant with us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.15, 16. the holy ghoſt is a witneſs to us: for after he had ſaid before, <hi>This is the Covenant that I will make with them: I will put my Laws into their hearts,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are baptized into his name, we are baptized into his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, religion, faith, doctrine.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What Scriptures prove unto us the Trinity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe following: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.7. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. In the New Teſtament, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.32, 33. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.3, 13, 14, 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. The ſame name of Jehovah, and the ſame works, are aſcribed to each perſon.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the attributes of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. There are many of them; as, 1. Spirituality, whereby he cannot be touched, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.29. <hi>For a Spirit hath not fleſh nor bones;</hi> nor can he be ſeen, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Whom no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Eternity, whereby he was from everlaſting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.2. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41271:5"/> the mountains were brought forth, from everlaſting to everlaſting thou art God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Unchangeableneſs: There's <hi>no ſhadow of turning</hi> with God, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.29. Repentance attributed to God, ſignifies no change in Gods nature, but in his actions mutably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed from eternity. God is fain to ſpeak to us as Nurſes to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children, liſpingly, becauſe they cannot underſtand perfect ſpeech.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Omnipreſence; In that he is preſent everywhere, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.7. <hi>Whither ſhall I flee from thy preſence?</hi> and alſo knows every thing and perſon, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. <hi>All things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him, with whom we have to do:</hi> ſo that he knows the very motions of the will of man, even before they move.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Almightineſs; in that he is able to do whatſoever he pleaſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.6. <hi>Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed, that did he.</hi> Yea, he is able to do more then he pleaſeth to do; he could have raiſed up of ſtones children to <hi>Abraham.</hi> Matth. 3.9. He could have given Chriſt 12 legions of Angels. <hi>Job</hi> 42.2.</p>
            <p n="6">6. His Self-ſufficiency; in that he is compleat in himſelf, not needing any thing the creature can do, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>I am God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. His Knowledg; whereby God doth perfectly know himſelf, and by himſelf, all other things that are, were, ſhall be, or can be; and that not ſucceſſively, as men do, but by one act of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Job</hi> 42.2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.17.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Will of God; whereby he wills in a holy manner, and works all things according to the counſel thereof, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the parts of Gods Kingdom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two: 1. his decree: 2. the execution of it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods decree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is Gods everlaſting determination and purpoſe concerning all things and perſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.28. <hi>To do whatſoever thy hand and thy counſel determined before to be done.</hi> Eph. 1.11. <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated according to the purpoſe of him, who worketh all things after the counſel of his owne will.</hi> And as God decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning all things and perſons, ſo doth he decree the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place, time, means, and manner, Act. 27.31. <hi>Except
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41271:6"/> theſe abide in the Ship, ye cannot be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Predeſtination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is Gods fore-ordaining all reaſonable creatures, whether Angels or Men, to an everlaſting eſtate either of ſalvation or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, 1 Theſ. 5.9. <hi>God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtaine ſalvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of Predeſtination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two: 1. Election, which is Gods appointing ſome to Salvation through Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. <hi>He made known the riches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy which he had prepared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory.</hi> Eph. 1.5. <hi>Having choſen us in him before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Reprobation; which is Gods appointing ſome, both Men and Angels to deſtruction, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. there are ſome <hi>Veſſels to diſhonour.</hi> Rom. 9.22. <hi>To ſhew his wrath and make his power known, he endured with much long ſuffering the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is there no cauſe or inducement of Election in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected themſelves, or of Reprobation in the Reprobate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>He hath mercy on whom he will have mercy; and whom he will, he hardeneth.</hi> 2 Tim. 1.9. <hi>He hath called us with an holy calling, according to his own purpoſe and grace.</hi> Eph. 1.9. <hi>He made known unto us the myſtery of his will, according to his good pleaſure which he had purpoſed in himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not Chriſt the cauſe of our Election?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, not of Gods decreeing of it, for that he did of his own free-will; but of the execution of it: that is, our Salvation is for and through Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. <hi>He hath choſen us in him, before the foundation of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not ſin the cauſe of reprobation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for then all men ſhould be Reprobate, when God foreſaw that all would be ſinners: but ſin is the cauſe of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of reprobation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What uſe are we to make of our election?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſerves to humble us, that we had nothing of our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſhould breed in us love to God, for his love to us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It comforts, that our Salvation ſtandeth not in our ſelves,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41271:6"/> who dayly might loſe it; but in Gods unchangeable decree.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether is God, decreeing the works of the wicked, the author of ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: though God decrees the ſinful works of the wicked (for elſe they had not been) as the Jewes crucifying of Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. <hi>Him, being delivered by the determinate counſel and foreknowledg of God,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> ſelling into <hi>Egypt,</hi> Gen. 45.7, 50, 20. yet is nothing ſin, as God decreeth it, or commandeth it: <hi>Abraham's</hi> killing of <hi>Iſaak,</hi> being commanded of God, was a duty; which elſe, God forbiding it, was a ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gods decreeing of ſin, being a way to manifeſt the glory of Gods Juſtice, is a good thing.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the execution of Gods decree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It's an action of God, working all things in time, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his decree, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of the execution of Gods decree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two: 1. Creation. 2. Providence.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to create?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To bring a thing from no being, to being <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. Alſo, to bring in a form created of nothing, into a praeexiſtent matter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did God create all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By his Word; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. <hi>By the word of the Lord, were the heavens made:</hi> alſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3, <hi>&amp;c. Let there be light, and there was light. Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>The worlds were framed by the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what made he all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of nothing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Things which are ſeen, were not made of things which do appear.</hi> Which plainly appears, in that they are ſaid to be <hi>made in the beginning,</hi> that is, when there was nothing but God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. It was either made of the eſſence of God, or of nothing: but Gods eſſence is indiviſible; <hi>ergo,</hi> of nothing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How long was God in creating the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Six days, and reſted the ſeventh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.11. <hi>In ſix days the Lord made Heaven and Earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeventh day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was God ſo long in creating the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we might not lightly paſs over the works of God, which he was ſo long in creating.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41271:7"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Gods creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It's Gods action, whereby he made Nature, and all things in nature, whether ſubſtances or accidents, in the ſpace of ſix days; for his own glory, and happineſs of his Elect. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What grounds have we to believe there is a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. From Scripture, becauſe nothing falls out without the determinate counſel of God; no, not the crucifying of the Son of God, Act. 4.28. to do <hi>whatſoever thy hand and thy counſel determined before to be done.</hi> Matth. 10.29, 30, 31. not a <hi>hair falls from our heads,</hi> nor a <hi>ſparrow to the ground, without the will of our Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The providence of God is ſeen. 1. In making innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contrarieties ſerve to one end; as heat and cold, light and darkneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> the uſe of man. 2. From the reaſonable actions of unreaſonable creatures; as the ſhifting Countryes according to the ſeaſon of the year. 3. From the dependence of callings and countryes one upon another. 4. The fitting one thing for another: man hath an eye; colour is the object of it, light diſcovers the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, the air is a clear body through which it is ſeen. 5. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident proviſion made for all the creatures, as in bringing ſprings of water to all towns; the earth alſo bringing forth graſſe for every creature. 6. The fit rewards and puniſhments that are beſtowed and inflicted on the deeds of men, ſo that no wicked man can out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run Juſtice, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.30. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Haman</hi> ſeeking to hang <hi>Mordecai,</hi> is hanged. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Act.</hi> 12.22.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But if there be a Providence in the world, how comes it that ill men have ſo much proſperity and good men ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The proſperity of wicked men, tends to further the decree of God to their deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.32. <hi>The proſperity of fools ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> Moreover, the adverſity good men endure, is very profitable in many particular reſpects; as, to wean them from the world, and to keep their hearts humble; and that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing empty of the creature, may the more faſten upon God: ſo that good men have acknowledged their adverſity good for them, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.71. <hi>It is good for me, that I have been afflicted.</hi> Rom. 8.28. <hi>All things work together for good to them;</hi> therefore the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41271:7"/> adverſity is for their good: ſo that God doth ſo diſpoſe his rewards to his people, and puniſhments to the wicked, that, to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, it never happens ill to the Godly, or well to the wicked in this life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Providence of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is an outward action of God, whereby he doth govern and diſpoſe all and every thing which is made, both creatures and their actions, and faculties, according to the counſel of his will, that in every thing he may be glorified: As honours, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6, 7. Puniſhments, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. periods of Kingdomes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21. The wills of men, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.23. yea of the greateſt of men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Kings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. the counſels of men, as <hi>Achitophel,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.14. yea, the ſmalleſt thing, as a Sparrows falling, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.30. yea, the moſt accidental thing, as the killing of a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.13. yea, the lot caſt into the lap, is wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of by him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.33.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of Gods Providence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three: 1. The keeping the being of things in their kindes, in a continued ſucceſſion, as long as he ſees good, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>In him we live and move, and have our being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His government; whereby as a Monarch he governs all things, according to the liberty of his own will: ſo that when any creature goes according to the liberty of its will, it is becauſe God ſuffers it ſo to do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His ordination, or appointment; whereby God orders, brings, and diſpoſes all things, and the actions of things, how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly ſoever they may ſeem to be, to certain ends, according as it ſeemeth good to him; for the bringing about of which ends, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appointeth means.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is the providence of God converſant about ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. God preſerves that nature and will, that produces ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions. God hath a concurrence about ſinful actions, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.8. <hi>It was not you that ſent me hither, but God.</hi> Deut. 2.30. <hi>God hardened the Spirit of</hi> Sihon <hi>King of</hi> Heſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon. Pſal. 105.25. <hi>God changed the mindes of the</hi> Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>that they hated his people.</hi> But as in a chain that breaks, there is no link in fault but that which breaks; ſo in theſe concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41271:8"/> of cauſes, none is to be blamed but the next and immediate cauſe, which is the will of man; ſo that though God will the being, yet man alone wills the nature of ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the poſitive actions of God, in and about ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three: 1. His withdrawment of his help and grace from the creature; both the help of light, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.4. <hi>The Lord hath not given you an heart to perceive, and eyes to ſee;</hi> and alſo the help of ſupportance; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.31. Hezekiah <hi>was left of God to his pride, that he might know what was in his heart:</hi> which two helps being withdrawn, the creature ſins neceſſarily, but voluntarily; ſo that as the Sun cauſes darkneſs, not by overcaſting the air, but by hiding his light, as the ſtaffe falls to the ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not forced by the hand, but only forſaken of it; ſo God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing either light or ſupportment, man ſins. God, who ſuffers ſin, hath the power of hindering, without any obligation to us; and man hath the power of doing, without any compulſion: the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in God is without fault, the action in man without excuſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God works about ſin, by removing the impediments that hindered us from ſinning. God took away good <hi>Jehoiada,</hi> and then <hi>Joaſh</hi> ſhewed his wickedneſs, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.17. So God takes away a Maſter or Father, that kept ſuch a perſon from wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; who being removed, his wickedneſs appears.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God works about ſin, by ſetting before us objects, whereby he knows our corruption will be enticed, as a beautiful woman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an unchaſt perſon, wine or beer before a Drunkard.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God works about ſin by ſetting bounds to ſin, that it ſhall go ſo far, and no further, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.10. <hi>The remainder of wrath ſhalt thou reſtrain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. God works about ſin, in that he preſerves the perſon, nature, and faculties of the ſinner, even whiles he is in ſinning, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>In him we live, and move:</hi> as an horſ-man driving a lame horſe, is the cauſe of his going, not of his halting; ſo is God the cauſe of our moving, though not of the ſinfulneſs in our moving.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What uſe may we make of Gods providence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. See, that nothing befalls unto thee by chance; if we take chance as a cauſe in oppoſition to God, as the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> took it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To perſwade us to the uſe of prayer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.12. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.4</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41271:8"/>3. To free the heart from diſquieting carefulneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.32, 34.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Eye God in all thy affaires, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.15. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Not to fear the terrors of men, and ſo neglect duty, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28, 29.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To comfort us, that we are in covenant with him, that ſits at the ſtern, and governs all.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To comfort us in reſpect, 1. of our poor condition, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.7. 2. againſt enemyes plots, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.31, 33. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.24. 3. againſt fear of danger, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Job</hi> 29.4.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To work patience in afflictions, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.9. <hi>Job.</hi> 1.20, 21.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In what condition did God create man at firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In an holy and happy condition, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>God made man upright:</hi> which uprightneſs conſiſted in a perfect conformity of the faculties of the ſoul, and members of the body, to the will of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Did man continue in that ſtate wherein he was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: <hi>All have ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God,</hi> Rom. 3.23. Rom. 5.12. <hi>By one man ſin entred into the world, and death by ſin, and ſo death paſſed upon all men, in whom all have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What death did Adams ſin procure? was it only a temporal death, or was it not alſo eternal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Adams ſin procured to his poſterity eternal death, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of deſert: <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>If through the offence of one, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be dead, much more the grace of God, and the gift by grace, hath abounded unto many.</hi> As the grace of God, &amp; gift by grace, abounded unto many, that is, to eternal life, and to remiſſion of ſins; ſo the offence on the contrary, abounded unto eternal death: and ſo it is ſet down, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. that <hi>as ſin hath reigned unto death, even ſo might grace reign through righteouſneſs, unto eternal life, by Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, As the one is, ſo is the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as the juſtification is, by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> ſuch is the condemnation by the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41271:9"/>
            <p>But the juſtification by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> is a juſtification of life, that is, of or to eternal;</p>
            <p>Therefore the condemnation by the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> is a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to eternal death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, as by the offence of one, the judgment came upon all men to condemnation; even ſo by the righteouſneſs of one, the free gift came upon all men to juſtification of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any man object, <hi>that it's againſt equity that eternal death ſhould be inflicted for another man's ſin;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid againſt temporal death: it's as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt that natural life ſhould be taken away for the ſin of another; yet the Objectors, whether <hi>Socinians</hi> or <hi>Arminians,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The will of God is the rule of righteouſneſs; and if <hi>Adam</hi> would enter into ſuch an agreement with God, that if he ſtood, he and all his poſterity ſhould ſtand eternally; and if he fell, he and his poſterity ſhould periſh eternally: Who hath any thing to reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it? <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.7. the words are, <hi>They like</hi> Adam <hi>have tranſgreſſed the Covenant:</hi> ſo you have it varied in the margin. So that a Covenant paſſed betwixt God and <hi>Adam,</hi> for the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation whereof on <hi>Adams</hi> part, he and his incur'd eternal death: and we hold it equitable in the Courts of men, that for the treaſon of the Father, the Poſterity ſmarts alſo. <hi>Levi,</hi> in the loynes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> is ſaid to pay tithes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.9.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What did</hi> Adam <hi>paſſe over to his poſterity, beſides tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and eternal death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Beſides their being children of wrath (that is, not only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with whom God is angry, but upon whom his wrath abides, <hi>John</hi> 3.36.) they are <hi>children of wrath by nature,</hi> Eph. 2.3. ſignifying, not only that we are curſed, but that we are ſo by nature or birth; <hi>natura</hi> being derived <hi>a naſcendo,</hi> from being born. Of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> it might be ſaid, They were liable to wrath; but it could not be ſaid they were children of wrath: it might be ſaid they were, upon their fall, curſed; but it could not be ſaid they were born curſed. So that beſides temporal and eternal death, there is a viciouſnes of nature that paſſeth from <hi>Adam,</hi> to all his poſterity: ſo that as a creature begotten, partakes of the nature of the beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as an horſe of the nature of an horſe; ſo we partake of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41271:9"/> nature of our firſt Parents all along: ſo that <hi>no man can bring a clean thing out of an unclean,</hi> Job 14.4. for, <hi>we were ſhapen in wickedneſs, and in ſin did our mother conceive us,</hi> Pſal. 51.5. ſo that naturally we are <hi>eſtranged from God from the womb, ſpeaking lyes as ſoon as we can ſpeak,</hi> Pſal. 58.3. The looking-glaſſe of our <hi>miſery</hi> we may ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9. to the 20. which the Apoſtle applyes to himſelf, as well as others, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>What, are we better then they?</hi> (that is, by nature) <hi>No, in no wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay we become guilty by imitation only, as one Ox learns to plow by the ſight of another, is moſt falſe: For corrupt nature teaches many perſons evill, for which they never ſaw example; as <hi>Cain</hi> when he killed <hi>Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſay the immediate will of the ſinner is abſolutely neceſſary to conſtitute ſin, is to tye the Creator to the Law of the creature, who had a ſoveraigne power in himſelf, to propoſe what Law he pleaſed unto his creature.</p>
            <p>To ſay there is no ſuch defilement upon our natures, becauſe our conſciences accuſe us not for it; no more doth our conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe us for ſins of ignorance, and many other ſins; yet will we ſay they are not ſins? The conſciences of the <hi>Jewes</hi> did not condemn them for not dwelling in Boothes, in the feaſt of the ſeventh month, which they had omitted welnigh a thouſand years, from the days of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the days of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Neh. 8.14. to the 18. was it therefore not a ſin?</p>
            <p>And whereas ſome ſay, They cannot ſee how the ſin of our firſt Parents ſhould be both a ſin and a puniſhment: was not <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh's</hi> hardneſs of heart both a ſin and a puniſhment? Was not the Idolatry of the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> Rom. 1.21, 23, 24, 26, 28.</p>
            <p>Q. Whereas ſome ſay, <hi>No Infant, no not of the Heathens, is damned meerly for original ſin;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We know nothing of their damnation, but we ſpeak of the deſert of original ſin. I rather incline to judge of their ſalvation, they dying in Infancy, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Of ſuch is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> The innocency of all Infants (in reſpect of actual ſins) whether of heathen or chriſtian Parents, is the ſame: they may be ſaved, as the elect Angels are ſaved; or elſe God may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give that offence without ſatisfaction: for if that power be in a creature, to forgive a debt without payment, much more is it in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41271:10"/> God: and I humbly ſuppoſe there cannot be a more fit object to exerciſe the ſame, and to bring it into act, then towards poor dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants.</p>
            <p>But that which I moſt incline to, concerning the ſalvation of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants, is, that though God can pardon dying infants without ſatisfaction, yet that he will not, becauſe Chriſt Is the way to the Father, and <hi>No man comes to the Father, without Chriſt,</hi> John 14.6. Now Chriſt's ſatisfaction becomes effectual through be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving only, to them that have the power of believing; but to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infants, it may become effectual by bare applying, without believing, becauſe infants cannot believe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.39. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.11. That there is ſome way of ſalvation for infants, the Scripture ſpeaks, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.15, 16. but for any other way of ſalvation for them beſides Chriſt his ſatisfaction, we know not; nor for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance of ſatisfaction in behalfe of infants any other way, then by bare application on the Mediators part, and acceptation on Gods part, I cannot conceive. And ſhould infants be damned meerly for original ſin, then ſhould God deal more ſeverely with poor dying infants, then with the Devils, who were condemned to hell only for actual ſins.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth our natural defilement reſide?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In every faculty of ſoul, and member of body, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. <hi>They are all gon aſide, they are altogether become filthy.</hi> So that the whole man ſtands in need to be ſanctified, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.23. the Underſtanding is full of blindneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.2. the Will full of rebellion, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.40. and 8.44. the Affections of diſorder, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5. the Conſcience of benummedneſs and other defilements, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. the Ears full of filthy liſtnings, the Eyes full of wanton ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein doth our natural defilement conſiſt, which we drew from our firſt Parents?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In an averſnes to every thing that is good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. and 58.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a proneneſs to every thing that is evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5. So that corruption takes occaſion from the holy law of God, to ſtir us up to ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.8, 13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came Adams ſin to ſeize upon his poſterity?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41271:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That man by nature is wholly ſinful, nothing is more plain: but the manner how he came to be ſo, is hard to underſtand. Now as when we are fallen into a ditch, we ſtand not queſtioning ſo much how we fell in, as how to get out; ſo ſhould we ſee how to get out of this ſinful condition.</p>
            <p>But, to anſwer, ſome ſay the Parent begets the ſoul as well as body: but God is called <hi>the Father of Spirits,</hi> Heb. 12.9. See alſo Zach. 12.1. Num. 27.16. Eccleſ. 12.7. Either the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in generation conveyes part of his ſoul, and ſo the ſoul ſhould be diviſible, contrary to the nature of ſpirits, which are not quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titative; or he conveys his whole ſoul, and ſo the Parent ſhould be without a ſoul; or elſe ſouls multiply: which is more then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels do.</p>
            <p>Therefore, 1. we become guilty by imputation, or by Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination: in one man, God ordained to adorn us all, if he ſtood; in one man, he ordained to ſtrip us all, if he fell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By natural propagation or generation of that moſt filthy nature which <hi>Adam</hi> had after his fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Adam begat a ſon in his own likeneſs, after HIS IMAGE.</hi> What image had <hi>Adam</hi> then, ſave a corrupt image? <hi>Job</hi> 14.4. <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?</hi> no body: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Behold, I was ſhapen in wickedneſs, and in ſin did my mother conceive me.</hi> So that ſinful man (by man, I mean both man and woman; who though they be two in ſex, yet are they one in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and one in wedlock) I ſay, ſinful man begets ſinful man: ſo that ſin is in the ſeed inbidingly, as fire is in the flint, as ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. This power that the body ſhould have over the ſoul, being above nature, may be aſcribed to Gods juſtice, puniſhing <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, in his baſe ſubjecting of his ſpirit to the fleſh. Through the ſeed, hereditary diſeaſes of Gout, Stone, Conſumption, Leproſy, are conveyed, which are inviſible; and why may not ſin be convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the father to the childe, in generation?</p>
            <p>Though this anſwer may be ſatisfactory to many, yet I reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the former, that we become guilty by imputation.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How doth it appear, that</hi> Adams <hi>ſin is imputed to all his poſterity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It appears, 1. Becauſe ſin was in the world before there was a Law given on <hi>Sinai,</hi> as appears, in that all <hi>Adams</hi> poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41271:11"/> were liable unto a temporal death, which is the fruit of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.13. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill the Law, ſin was in the world; ſo that death raigned, from the time of Adam to Moſes,</hi> verſ. 14. now ſin would not have been imputed (and conſequently death) when there is no Law. Now if you ſay, What Law was there before <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, without which ſin would not have been imputed? I anſwer, Though there was the Law of Nature writ in our hearts by Nature; yet the Law the Apoſtle there ſpeaks of, was this, mentioned <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. That by one man <hi>(Adam)</hi> ſinning, all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſhould ſin in him, &amp; by that one ſin of that one man <hi>(Adam)</hi> death ſhould come upon all. He ſpeaks not one word of the Law of Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It appears that <hi>Adams</hi> ſin is imputed to all his poſterity, from the death of infants. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Death reigned from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam to Moſes</hi> (and ſo along) <hi>even over them who had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after the ſimilitude of Adams tranſgreſſion;</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant otherwiſe, then of infants, who had not ſinned actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as <hi>Adam</hi> had: ſo that the Apoſtle argues thus:</p>
            <p>Where death reigned without guilt of their own actual ſin, there neceſſarily muſt be an imputation of the guilt of the firſt ſin.</p>
            <p>But before the Law, death reigned over thoſe that had no guilt, from their own actual ſins, (meaning little infants, that could not ſin actually, after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion:)</p>
            <p>Therefore the guilt of the firſt ſin, is neceſſarily imputed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; and if ſo infants, much more to grown perſons, and ſo to all.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What may we learn hence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That there is <hi>a ſinning after the ſimilitude of Adams tranſgreſſion,</hi> or actually. 2. That there is a ſinning which is <hi>not</hi> after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, or imputatively; which is called <hi>original ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is original ſin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the corruption of all mankinde, by the fall of our firſt Parents, naturally propagated or derived unto all, making them guilty of temporal and eternal death, and other puniſhments, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs forgiveneſs be made in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 13, 14, 15. It's called <hi>original ſin,</hi> becauſe it was in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the beginning, from the firſt man that ever was.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41271:11"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What way is their to come out of this miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Only by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21, 22.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The eternal Son of God, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.2. made man, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many are the Offices of Chriſt in relation to his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are three.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His Kingly office, whereby he rules in his Church, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6. and in the hearts of his people, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Prophetical office, whereby he revealing his Fathers will, wee are to hear him in all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His Prieſtly Office, whereby he offers ſacrifice for the ſins of his people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſacrifice did Chriſt offer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His own body upon the Croſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why did Chriſt offer his own body upon the Croſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To make ſatisfaction for the ſins of all thoſe that believe on him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25, 26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a matrimonial act of the ſoul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.32. whereby I do not only believe that there was ſuch a perſon as one Jeſus Chriſt, who dyed and roſe at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> but I believe alſo that he dyed and roſe again for me: yea, my ſoul is willing to receive him, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. as my Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Jude</hi> 21.25. and to reſt upon his ſatisfaction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10, 11.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Whether doth Faith go before the forgiveneſs of ſins?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We are not firſt waſhed, and then believe; but in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-language we firſt believe, and afterwards are waſhed: hence we are ſaid to be juſtified by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. and to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. and Chriſt is ſet forth a reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through Faith in his blood, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. which blood, though it have ſufficient vertue to cleanſe us from our ſins, yet it doth not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41271:12"/> actually purge any, unleſs it be applyed: when it is once applyed, that the ſoul looks believingly and mournfully upon him whom he hath pierced, in that day is there a Fountain ſet open to that ſoul, the Fountain of Chriſt his blood, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But whether is Faith or Repentance firſt in the ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Though Faith be in order before Repentance, yet in reſpect of time they are both together in the ſoul; for in the ſame moment the Children of God believe that Chriſt was crucified for their ſins, they melt under the ſight of their ſins, which were the cauſe of his crucifying, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.12 13. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth the ſoul act in receiving Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is not onely an aſſent of the underſtanding that Jeſus is the Chriſt that came into the World to ſave ſinners, which may be in wicked men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. and Devils, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. but there is alſo an act of the will, whereby God offering his Son as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to be our Teacher, as a King to take us into his Government, as our Prieſt, by his death and interceſſion to waſh away our ſins; we look upon this offer as worthy of all acceptation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. and ſo receive Chriſt to be under his teachings, as our Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. reſt and repoſe our ſelves upon his Sacrifice and ſatisfaction, as our Prieſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. put our ſelves under his Government, and ſubject our wills to his will, as our King, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. This accepting Chriſt by the will, is that very receiving mentioned, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. becauſe whoſoever thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, have power to become the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the two parts of Chriſt his Prieſthood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. His death upon the Croſs, whereby in reſpect of Gods foreknowledge, Chriſts merit, and Gods acceptation, he bore the ſins of all the Elect upon the Croſs, ranſoming them to God by his death. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Reſurrection from the dead, together with his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in Heaven, whereby as an Advocate he pleades their cauſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. appearing in the preſence of God for them, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 9.24. preſenting the merits of his own death, whoſe blood ſpeaketh good things for them, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 9.24. So that he is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41271:12"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may a Believer know that Chriſt is his Advocate or Interceſſor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hereby do we know that we know him ſo to be, if we keep his Commandments, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 2, 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth a Believer keep the Commandments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. He keepeth them in his head Chriſt, in whoſe fleſh ſin was condemned, that the righteouſneſs of the Law might be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He keeps them intentionally, having a reſpect to every one of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. without ſlighting or deſpiſing any of them; ſeeing the Scripture ſets down, that the ſlighting or deſpiſing any of a mans wayes, doth declare him to be as yet under the ſtate of death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.13. and <hi>chap.</hi> 19.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In that he will not deliberately ſin againſt Conſcience, for the eſcaping of Croſſes, or obtaining of enjoyments, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17. having a full purpoſe in his heart (through the aſſiſtance of grace) to chuſe affliction rather then iniquity, <hi>Job</hi> 36.21.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meaſure of love muſt we love the Lord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We muſt love him with a ſoveraign love, better then Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, Lands and Living Wife and Children; yea, and our own Lives, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What denial of Chriſt is that which excludes a ſoul out of Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Habitual denial, when we, for the ſaving of our Lands, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Country or Lives, have a purpoſe to deny Chriſt, or any part of his truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32, 33.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What way it there to prevent this habitual denial of Chriſt, which is ſo dangerous and deſtructive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To learn to deny our ſelves in ſuch a meaſure, that in the Lords ſtrength we reſolve to take up every Croſs that comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and our duty, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.23. and to hate the beſt enjoyment we have, as friends, liberty, eſtate, yea and life it ſelf, if we cannot hold them and the Lord together, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26, 27. So that we are reſolved in no wiſe in a plain Commandment to ſin againſt our Conſcience, but are reſolved to chuſe a fiery furnace, rather then worſhip a golden image. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41271:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A change of heart, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22, 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1, 2. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we turn from all ſin with an hatred thereof, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128. purpoſing to walk in newneſs of life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.106.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What are the fruits of Repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Apoſtle ſets down ſome, 2 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 7.11. as a care of pleaſing God in every thing; alſo a fear of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing him in any thing; alſo a clearing of our ſelves both before God, not reſting till we have got aſſurance of the pardon of our ſins; and clearing our ſelves before men, in a godly courſe of life; alſo a deſire to eye God in all things; alſo a zeal, rejoycing when his name is honoured, and ſorrowing when it is diſhonoured; alſo an indignation againſt ſin, in a friend as well as an enemy, in a rich man as well as poor; alſo revenge againſt our ſelves, in that, as we have abuſed Gods bleſſings to our own luſts, ſo we endeavour hereafter to ſpend them to his Honour.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture reveal concerning ſpirituall death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It reveales unto us that we are under a threefold death.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A death of guiltineſs, whereby we are bound over to eternal death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.32. <hi>John</hi> 5.24. being wrapt therein by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin and our own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A death of filthineſs, whereby naturally we all lye wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in carnal courſes, though ſome are more deeply in them then others, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 3, 3. This life of holineſs was alſo loſt by <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.25.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A death of diſcomfort, whereby naturally we are deprived of that ſweet Communion and enjoyment of God, which <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocency, and regenerate men have in part, and glorified Saints have in fulneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What doth the Scripture reveal concerning ſpirituall life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It reveals unto us, that there are three parts of ſpiritual life in oppoſition to this death:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The life of juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. ſo that whereas we are all dead men by offending the Law, when God pardons we are alive, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The life of Sanctification, when a man is quickened up to all the wayes of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11, 13.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41271:13"/>3. The of comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.6. when the ſoul enjoyes a life in Gods favour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. looking upon the abſence thereof as death it ſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.7.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What neceſſity is there of ſpirituall life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is ſo needful, that without it there is no Salvation, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. All the Body of Chriſt being living ſtones, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. without this, thy converſion is nothing, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5. thy Faith nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.26. thy Hope nothing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. thy Repentance nothing, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.18. and thy duties of Religion nothing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.18. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.15. yea, if thou beeſt without this, thou haſt no ſhare (as yet) in Chriſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What kinde of thing is ſpiritual life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As it hath reſpect to change of heart, there is an unſeen working of the ſpirit upon the ſouls of Believers, ſo that as there goes an hidden quality from the Loadſtone to the iron, that draws the iron to it; ſo is there a power goes from Chriſt to draw the ſoul off from all ſinful purpoſes unto himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>John</hi> 12.31. So that the ſoul exalts Chriſt, though with the loſs of all luſts and all enjoyments, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what faculty of the ſoul is ſpiritual Life ſeated?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Though whereſoever ſpiritual life is, it ſhowes forth its acts and operations, (as the natural life doth) in the whole man; yet as the natural life is more eminently in the head and heart: ſo is this ſpiritual life more eminently in the faculties of the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Will, Conſcience, Affections and Memory.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may a perſon know his underſtanding it made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When he doth not onely think of divine truths, <hi>John</hi> 5.39. and approve them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.18. which natural men may do; but alſo applies them to his own Conſcience, <hi>Job</hi> 5.27. meditates of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. ponders them, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.19. remembers them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.55. judges aright of Gods wayes; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.128. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13, 14. and is often inventing and deviſing how to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, and to keep Conſcience pure, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 14.22. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may a man know his will is made alive to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Though the Saints of God have drawn comfort from their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41271:14"/> willing good, when they could do no more but will, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18, 19, 25. yet may there be wiſhings and wouldings in a heart often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and yet it remain carnal, as in <hi>Balaam, Numb.</hi> 23.10. and many others: now becauſe many thouſands deceive themſelves by their wiſhings and wouldings, know that wiſhing or willing good is an Argument of ſpiritual life,</p>
            <p n="1">1. VVhen the will brings forth earneſt and diligent endeavors, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 32. againſt all hindrances and pull-backs whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVhen the will of a man is ſet for good abſolutely, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.145. <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.8. though it expoſe him to the Croſs, and he gave no thanks, but be hated of men for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. VVhen the inclinations and diſpoſitions of the heart are for God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.112. that what other men do with a dead heart, he doth with a willing diſpoſition.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By the chuſings and refuſings of the heart; when we chuſe the wayes of God before all other wayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30, 173. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4. and refuſe the wayes of all ſin in the purpoſe of the heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.101, 104. but when men have good things put to them by the word and Conſcience, and in the purpoſe and frame of their heart refuſe them, this argues a dead will, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the cleaving of the heart; when the heart ſticks ſo to its duty, that nothing can pull it off, neither bonds nor impriſonment, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. ſo that though violence of torturing temptations may ſeem to carry the ſoul off in a fit, as in ſome of the Martyrs, yet in the habit of the heart it ſticks ſo to God and his Word, that nothing can unſettle the habit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.31. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10. though tentation may unſettle an act.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By the groanings and ſighings of the heart under corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.5. <hi>David</hi> out of the unwillingneſs of his fleſh, fetch'd a groan, ſaying, <hi>O that my wayes were made direct!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. By the reachings of the will; living wills uſe to reach after God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13. as a man that reaches as high as he can, and ſtrives to reach higher; he believes in ſome meaſure, and would believe more; oppoſes every known ſin, and would oppoſe it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41271:14"/> more; follows all goodneſs, and would follow it more.</p>
            <p n="8">8. By the intentions of the heart, when they are ſet for God, ſo that the ſoul ſaith thus, So that I may keep cloſe to God, and keep my conſcience pure, and may not be carried away with the world; this is that I deſire: ſo that as carnal men make honour and pleaſure, and that which leads thereto, their ends: ſo Saints make God, and that which lead to him, their end.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may a man know his conſcience is made alive to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Urgency of conſcience to preſs the ſoul to its duty, is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of ſpiritual life, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.18. nor yet trouble of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before or after the committing of ſin, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.26. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.14. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.41. Yea, conſcience awakened may make a man go againſt all outward by-reſpects, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.4. and make a man look at God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.29. <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But then is the conſcience alive, when not onely conſcience doth his duty, but makes a man do his duty towards God and Man, whether conſcience do it with much adoe, or little adoe; as to believe with all the heart, to love God ſoveraignly, to ſerve God ſincerely, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When the conſcience doth not onely excuſe a man in part, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.6, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. but excuſes him full out, that he ſtands guitleſs by faith in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2. and that every purpoſe of his heart is ſet againſt every ſin, and for every duty, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When we are glad our conſcience is ſo buſie with us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.7. yea we call upon our conſcience to be buſie with us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may we know our affections are made alive to God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. When our principall treaſure is in heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.20. and our affections are ſet upon it, not upon the world, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12. That though worldly occaſions may put off the heart from heaven for a time, yet no ſooner are theſe employments over, but the heart endeavours after its former enjoyment of God: ſo that as the affections of dead men are ever and anon upon the world, becauſe they have a dead and worldly frame of heart; ſo the affections of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41271:15"/> men ſpiritually alive, are ever and anon upon God, becauſe they have a quickned and heavenly frame of heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. VVhen the heart can reliſh good things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5. So that as carnal men ſavour profit and pleaſure, and carnal contents; ſo the affections alive can ſavour communion with God, the face of God, the word of God, the ſweetneſs of a Spiritual duty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the heart eſteems God above all enjoyments, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25, 26. So that thou wilt morgage any thing for God, and the things of God; ſo that thou wilt count his glory dearer then thy credit, duty to him dearer then life to thy ſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. to ſuch affections, the promiſe, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. grace, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.15. and Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. is pretious above all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When thy greateſt care is to pleaſe God, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8. and how to get thy heart weaned from the world, and how to keep conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence pure, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. and thy greateſt fear is to ſin againſt God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10. ſo that thou feareſt him above reproach, poverty, or death it ſelf, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may we know our memory it made alive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Whereas by Nature corrupt we are apt to remember fooliſh things, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.3. as fooliſh jeſts, and wrongs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done to us, and are apt to forget God and all his commands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.7. the Spirit brings good things to a regenerate memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. ſo that the ſoul remembers to practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.16. And as at other times he remembers his duty ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in time of tentation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ought to be the ground and motive of a Chriſtians obedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. The command of Chriſt, with is the bond of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.22.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The love of God, from whence our obedience ought to flow, <hi>John</hi> 14.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture reveal of the combat of the fleſh and ſpirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It tells us that the fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the fleſh; ſo that we cannot do the good that we would do, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What my comfort a regenerate man in this combat of Fleſh and Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41271:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This may comfort him, 1. That he hates the evil that he doth, and loves the good that he doth not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he delight in that law that forbids his evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.22. and conſents unto it that it is a good law, <hi>ver.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He groans under his evil as a moſt heavy burthen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. and doth not allow himſelf in the leaſt evil, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though his fleſh do too often ſerve the Law of ſin, yet in his mind or intention of his heart he ſtill doth ſerve the Law of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing many natural men have combats in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in reſpect of ſin, how ſhall I know that I combat aright?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The combats that Natural men have, are moſtly,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Betwixt Reaſon and ſenſuality; ſo many are ſorry they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refrain their uncleanneſs, drunkenneſs, gaming, becauſe they are contrary to reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or betwixt natural Conſcience, and natural Paſſions, as in <hi>Pilate,</hi> whoſe conſcience warned him not to paſs ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, yet he durſt not do otherwiſe, for fear he ſhould loſe <hi>Caeſars</hi> favour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Or betwixt ſome outward evil for a time, or ſome groſs ſin all their life long; mean time harbouring ſome ſecret darling-abomination, as the love of their eſtates, liberties and lives, more then Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Or betwixt a purpoſe of continuing in ſinfull pleaſures, and a deſire to enjoy eternal pleaſures, as in <hi>Balaam,</hi> who deſired to live in covetouſneſs, yet would fain have died the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; ſo is this combat ſometimes betwixt theſe ſinful pleaſures here, and the fear of eternal vengeance hereafter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Their combat, how hot ſoever, is ſtill joyned with a cuſtome and purpoſe of ſinning, ſo that they lay down the Cudgels to ſin, ſaying, This is my nature, and I muſt do it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p>Now the combat in regenerate men, is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Fierce, and in the purpoſe of the heart againſt all ſin, though ſometimes it be defective in ſome act or acts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this combat they diſallow the evil they do, not onely from a principle of natural conſcience (which in ſome ſins carnal men may do) but alſo from a principle of ſpiritual life, becauſe it is contrary to the life which they live.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41271:16"/>3. They groan under their evils with many a ſign and tear in ſecret yea ſuch evils as the world takes no notice of as dead-harted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs declining of affection to God, want of former feelings, hard neſs of heart, unbelief coldneſs and diſtraction in good duties, vain hopes, vain fears, carking caſes lumpiſhneſs in Gods ſervice, riſings of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge: alſo the tricks the ſoul hath had to keep off convincement in ſuffering times; alſo the by-ends in the good it hath done. One wears a chain as an ornament, another as a fetter, and would fain be rid of it; ſo wicked men wear their luſts as ornaments to them, but Gods people wear them as the heavieſt chain.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If in the combat the Fleſh get the upper hand, and they fall, they cannot be quiet till they have turned to God, and recovered their acquaintance with him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. but carnal men are not troubled but add ſin to ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.24.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether it be poſſible for a Chriſtian to be aſſured of his union with Chriſt, and of his acceptation into favour with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes: 1. becauſe the Scripture bids us prove our ſpirituall eſtate, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. Now the Spirit would not bid us ſearch for that which could not be found. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Scripture reveales unto us many evidences of our aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſome taken from our union with Chriſt, and ſome from the in-dwelling of the Spirit in us.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What markes or ſigns doth the Scripture reveal to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence our union with Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The moſt demonſtrative ſigne, or at leaſt one of them, is ſoveraigne love to God, to the Lord better then any enjoyment of Lands, Liberties, Life, Wife and Children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. &amp; 14.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. which evidence if you leave out, the ſoul may be deceived in others ſevered from this. For whoſoever believes in Chriſt, his faith doth work by love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4. yea by a love of this meaſure, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26, 27, 35.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the Witneſſes that witneſs a Chriſtians good condition to God-ward?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two: 1. The witneſs of Gods Spirit: 2. The witneſs of our regenerated Spirits, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. <hi>The Spirit beareth witneſs with our Spirit, that we are the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41271:16"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Spirit witneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It witneſſes God is our Father; for we having received the Spirit of adoption, thereby cry Abba Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. it witneſſes the things that are freely given us of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9, 12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>After what manner doth the Spirit witneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two wayes; Firſt, by the impreſſions and ſtamps which like a Seal upon the Wax, it maketh upon the ſoul, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the fruits and effects thereof.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What are the impreſſions or ſtamps the Spirit maketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are two: Firſt, the ſtamp of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> whereby the Spirit changeth the Saints into the image of God, from one glorious grace into another, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. ſo that as a ſeal deſtroyes that image that was in the Wax before, ſo doth the ſeal or ſtamps of the Spirit deſtroy corruption in the ſoul in reſpect of the reign of it, and ſet up grace in the reign thereof. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. This ſame ſtamp of <hi>Holineſs</hi> being throughout, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.23. and conſiſting in a change of the whole man, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. and eſpecially in a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the minde, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. and will, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. is one of the impreſſions of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the impreſſion of <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Feeling, Pſal.</hi> 51.8.12. this being given of the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. as an occaſional re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, not as daily food for the ſoul to feed upon, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.22. doth ſhew the Spirit of God is in us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. yet doth not the want of his feeling prove that the Spirit of God is not in us; for God doth ſometimes hide himſelf from the ſoul, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.8. the Spirit in reſpect of this feeling, is one of the <hi>three witneſſes</hi> that teſtifies Chriſt to be our Saviour, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>whether is a Chriſtians aſſurance and feeling all one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: The word and promiſe of a powerful, faithful, and willing God, with the Notes and Evidences of a Chriſtians good eſtate, as they are laid down in the Scripture, are the grounds of a Chriſtians aſſurance; and comfortable feelings are the Crown thereof. A poor deſerted ſoul that hath little feeling, may have a ſoveraign love of God, fear of ſin, and an abſolute purpoſe againſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41271:17"/> it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.18, 19. yea, he may have uprightneſs of heart, <hi>Job</hi> 1.1. compared with <hi>chap.</hi> 6.4. yea he may have faith in Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1. yea, an earneſt thirſting after Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. Now ſhall I have a purpoſe to deny credit, wealth and life for Chriſt, yea and have all the forementioned gracious fruits, and ſhall I not have grounds of aſſurance that my eſtate is good to God-ward? When Chriſt asked <hi>Peter</hi> whether he loved him, he did not ſay, Lord thou knoweſt we cannot tell whether we love thee or no; but ſaid, <hi>Thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whew doth the Spirit ſeal the ſoul with comfort?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, when the ſoul is caſt down in humiliation, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly longs for the light of Gods countenance, <hi>Job</hi> 22.29. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.19.</p>
            <p>Secondly, upon ſelf-denial of that which is pleaſant, or ſuffering that which is painful, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.27.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, after conflict with corruptions, or other temptations, and victory over them, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.17.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when a believer takes paines with his heart, and puts forth his ſtrength in duty, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 12.4.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What are the effects and fruits whereby the Spirit wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes his in-being in the ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are divers; as, 1. An inablement of the ſoul to do things above nature, as to love the Lord Soveraignly, to love our enemies, to love the godly for the Image of God in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Spirit is combating in us againſt all that is ſin, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. ſo that we do not onely ſuppreſs the ſame, but alſo luſt after graces contrary thereunto.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the beames of the Sun ſhew forth the preſence of the Sun, ſo the ſighs, groans, and meltings in holy hearts, evidence that the Spirit is in them, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the teſtimony of our own ſpirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the Teſtimony of a renewed Conſcience, witneſſing us no be in the ſtate of grace, upon ſufficient grounds <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe grounds?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe Faith evidences, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. That none can lay any thing to my Charge, ſeeing Chriſt did not onely dye for me, but roſe again, and aſcended into heaven making interceſſion for me, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. So that he appearing for me as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41271:17"/> my Advocate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. And his blood ſpeaking good things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24. he is not onely able to ſave me to the <hi>uttermoſt,</hi> though my ſins be great and many, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. but is alſo willing, in that he promiſes in no wiſe to caſt off them that come unto him, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. which my poor ſoul doth.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What other ground is there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> My union with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How knoweſt thou, thou art united with Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. By my ſoveraign love to him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By my being made a new Creature, and my crucifying the fleſh, with the luſts and affections thereof, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. which is not meant, as if there were no oldneſs of nature in me, or that every luſt were actually and perfectly dead; but it's meant thus, my luſts are crucified, and I am new intentionally, becauſe it is that I aime at, and ſtrive after daily.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He that is united to Chriſt, lives not in ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. He that abideth in him, ſins not; which is not meant ſimply of not ſinn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for no man lives that ſins not 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.46. therefore it is meant of a purpoſe of ſinning: hence thoſe in Chriſt are ſaid not to walk after the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. that is, though ſometimes they may ſlip, yet the conſtant purpoſe of their heart is after the guidance of the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He that abides in Chriſt, walkes as Chriſt walked, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6. with an <hi>as</hi> of ſimilitude, though not of equality, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7. he endeavours to follow Chriſt in every ſtep, though he cannot take ſuch long ſtrides. As a young writer begins and ends his lines, and makes his letters like his Maſter, though he cannot write ſo fair; ſo every Member of Chriſts body, having the ſame mind, (in his meaſure) that was in Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5. endeavours to follow Chriſt in all graces and duties, and his ſo walking is evidential unto him: and to every one that thus obeys Chriſt, he becomes the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or Cauſer of eternal ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He that abides in Chriſt, is fruitful, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5. which though Hypocrites may ſeem to imitate, yet the fruitfulneſs of Chriſtians is eaſily diſtinguiſhed, in that it's not from external motives, but from Chriſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.8. nor for ends ſelfiſh and baſe, but for Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other ground of aſſurance for the ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41271:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I have this ground that my ſins are forgiven me, becauſe I have the other branches of the new Covenant made over to me, as the taking away from me a ſtony hard heart, and my heart and the Commandment cloſes together, and that I know God with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing knowledge, and not onely with a bare notional knowledge; therefore I have this branch of the new Covenant, that my ſins and iniquities God will remember them no more, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11, 12. for all the branches of the new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant are undivided, and my ſoul truly repents, and therefore God hath promiſed faithfully to forgive, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.13. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. So that whatever evidences my repentance, the ſame alſo evidences the pardon of my ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other grounds of aſſurance have you for your ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I finde an univerſal change: in the underſtanding, from darkneſs to light, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. in the judgement, from falſe diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a right diſcerning, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. in the Conſcience from benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medneſs to tenderneſs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5. in the will, from wilfulneſs to evil, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. to willingneſs for good, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.19. in the imagination, from habitual running upon the World, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. to be often in Heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1, 2. in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, which formerly were lawleſs, now awed by the eye of God, <hi>Job</hi> 31.23.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing there may be changes, as from prophaneſs to civility, and from civility to a form of Religion without the power, how ſhall I know my change to be right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I know it to be a true change, becauſe I go from one contrary to another, that the things which I hated, now I love; and the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal courſes I loved, now I hate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. holy duties were tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, now they are delightful, and now my ſoul begins to reliſh that which formerly I loathed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other ground of aſſurance have you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This, that I have a true converſion, which appeares,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the humiliation and confuſion of ſpirit I have for living ſo long a ſtranger from God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. being ſorry I begun no ſooner in Gods wayes, and that ſince I have begun, I have made no greater haſte.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41271:18"/>2. By my high eſteem of my preſent condition, in a converted eſtate, though never ſo baſe, that I would not change my conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the greateſt man upon earth, that is a ſtranger from the Lord, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.39.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other ground of aſſurance have you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As the Saints of God of old have gathered comfort and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance from their uprightneſs, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. and <hi>Paul</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing from their uprightneſs and godly ſincerity, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. ſo we may gather aſſurance from them, when</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ordinarily and uſually look at the eye of God in the things we do, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.6.7. and have a deſire (if it might be) alwayes to look at his eye, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17. by-ends beings a grief unto us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uprightneſs is ſeen by a diſpoſition to part with whatſoever God commands, when we cannot hold Chriſt and ſuch enjoyment together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When the ſame ſins we avoid in publick, we avoid in ſecret, out of Conſcience to God, <hi>Job</hi> 31.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10. and the ſame duties we do before men, we labour to do them in ſecret before God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When a bare Command moves us to act in our duty, though no ſecond reſpects of credit or profit accompany, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.3. and contrary, though ſecond reſpects of credit and profit which are offered, move us to act againſt duty, yet we will not act, out of Conſcience of our duty to God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how do you alledge all the fore-named ſigns? do you make the ſoul to ſtay upon theſe as a righteouſneſs to anſwer divine juſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In no wiſe: but I make them evidences that I have the Spirit of Chriſt in my heart; and having the Spirit, I alſo have the blood of Chriſt, becauſe theſe are not ſevered one from the other in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that righteouſneſs which anſwers Divine Juſtice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It was the ſatisfaction of Chriſt upon the Croſs; for the merit or deſert whereof, God did not only forgive us our ſins, but did alſo blot out, take away, and by nailing to the Croſs, did tear all hand-writings of Moſaical or Ceremonial Ordinances, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41271:19"/> did publickly profeſs the miſery and guilt of the World, and alſo did blot out, take away, and tear the damnatory power of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law, which being contrary to us, did convince us of ſin, and condemn us for it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. So that as the Debter is quiet when his Debt is forgiven, and the Bond cancelled; ſo the heart of the Bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ever is quieted, when not onely all his ſins, both original and actual, are forgiven; but alſo all hand-writings which may witneſs the ſame againſt him, are taken away, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13, 14. yea, not onely ſo, but alſo the ſame Lord Jeſus did ſpoile, ſtrip, and diſarme the principalities and powers of Hell, of all that power whereby they proſecuted the bond of the Law againſt us, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. and made a triumphant ſhew of them ſo conquered to the Faith of the Believer, as the triumphant Conquerors of the World were wont (of old) to lead the Conquered bound before their triumphant Charets, all the people looking on, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. And as in battel, where the General and chief Commanders are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, the reſt of the Souldiery are alſo ſubdued; ſo with the Devils, whatſoever did war againſt us, was overcomed, as Law, Sin, Death, Hell, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. ſo that none can lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to live by Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To reſt on Gods promiſes for juſtification, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. for Sanctification, <hi>John</hi> 15.2. and for temporal things, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.10. So that whereas carnal men live by ſenſe, believing no further then they ſee, and live by their luſts, helping themſelves by indirect means in time of want and danger, a Chriſtian lives upon a promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.9, 10, 11. <hi>Eſther</hi> 4.4. <hi>Job.</hi> 13.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein is the life of faith ſeen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In ſundry particulars; as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In drawing life and quickening from Chriſt, as the branches draw ſap from the root, <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In believing pardon of ſin, notwithſtanding many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of aggravation alledged by Satan and Conſcience, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In comforting in afflictions: though I be afflicted, ſaith Faith, yet it is the hand of a wiſe God and tender Father, <hi>John</hi> 18.11. this Cup is a medicine out of a Fathers hand.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In propoſing God to the ſoul in the loſs of all: when there is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41271:19"/> nothing in the barn, nor in the field, faith ſees enough in God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Hab.</hi> 3:16, 17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. When friends dye, and Credit is gone, Faith tells the ſoul God lives, and there is praiſe with him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In making a perſon let go the beſt of enjoyments for God: as credit, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20. and eſtate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. and pleaſures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25. and life, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. and cauſing him to ſuffer the worſt of evils; as reproaches, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. baniſhment, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.10. and tortures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. out of Conſcience towards God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In making a perſon refuſe ſinful gaine, <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.21. when it might be had without any mans knowledge, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.6.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In keeping the ſoul from the uſe of unlawful means to come out of trouble, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9, 10. waiting till God open a door of deliverance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In eying God for a good iſſue out of the midſt of troubles, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.12. becauſe of his promiſe that he will never fail us, nor forſake us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In ſetting before the ſoul the recompence of reward, both in eternity of joy, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. and property of intereſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. all this is thine, ſaith Faith.</p>
            <p n="10">10. In freeing the ſoul from a ſlaviſh fear of death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4. men have found out comfort againſt other evils, as poverty, ſhame; but faith onely profeſſes the Cure of the fear of death.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41271:20"/>
               <head>Of Sins againſt Knowledge and Conſcience.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is it to ſin againſt knowledge or Conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is when we take the fulfilling of a luſt, or the performance of a duty into conſideration, and conſider motives againſt the ſin or to the duty; and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe motives that would ſtop us, yet we commit the ſin, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24. or omit the duty, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether are all ſins againſt Knowledge and Conſcience alike, or are ſome greater then others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The more a perſon conſiders the iſſues and events of ſuch a ſin before he commits it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. and the more conſultations thou haſt about it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.14. and the more warnings thou haſt againſt it, whether from God, Conſcience or men, and yet doſt commit it; the more hainous is thy ſin, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.18, 19. Yea, the more ſorrow and reluctancy in committing ſuch an evil, argues thou ſinneſt againſt greater knowledge, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.26. for this diſpleaſure of minde, ariſes, from the deep apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the evil then a doing from which thy knowledge would ſtop thee, but it cannot.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether are ſins committed againſt Conſcience and Knowledge pardonable?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, 1. Becauſe they are not the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe for the moſt voluntary ſins, a Sacrifice was to be offered, <hi>Levit.</hi> 6.8. There were Sacrifices to be offered for him that denyed a thing that was given him to keep, in the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; but if perſons perſecute the Truth againſt light, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, then there is no pardon for that ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5. and 10.26, 27, 28, 29. Yet though ſins againſt Conſcience are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable, yet this circumſtance, that ſuch a ſin was deliberately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt light, makes the ſoul more guilty than ordinarily the ſin committed therewith.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41271:20"/>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Wherein is the greatneſs of ſins againſt Knowledge ſoon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In divers reſpects, as 1. In ſuch ſins there is a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the power of Knowledge, and Juſtice of God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.30. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32, 33.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſuch ſins there is more of the Will, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12. hence <hi>Saul</hi> for ſinning againſt Conſcience was caſt off, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12. <hi>compared with</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.14, 26.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In ſuch ſins, there is a greater reſiſtance of that light the Spirit kindles in us, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> lying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that light the Spirit ſet up in them, were ſmit with ſudden death for ſinning ſo againſt their knowledge, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In ſins againſt Knowledge there are fewer pretences, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.22. In ſins of ignorance men pretend they know not duty; but here's no place for ſuch pretence, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.41.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We may ſee the greatneſs of ſuch ſins, from the ſtripes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to them, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.15. ſuch are beaten with many ſtripes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In that by ſuch ſins we do at once quench the fire of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and loſe the feelings of Gods Love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why do men venture upon ſins againſt knowledge, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are dangerous?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Union of the heart to ſome luſt, either of gain or pleaſure, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.10. <hi>compared with verſe</hi> 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Lothneſs to take up the Croſſes that lye in the way of duty. Hence perſons lye, and do other evils againſt conſcience, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Iob.</hi> 36.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Preſumptuous hope of Mercy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.21.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether may not a child of God fall into ſins againſt his knowledge and conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. There are ſome failings in duty, and ſtirrings of luſt in godly men, which are committed with knowledge, but not againſt it; for it is not in the power of knowledge to prevent them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 18. theſe evils ariſe on a ſuddain.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A godly man may ſin againſt his knowledge through ſtrength of paſſion, and ſuddain furreption, before he hath time to compoſe his heart; Conſcience in the act of it checks him, yet he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41271:21"/> cannot keep it back: ſo <hi>Peter</hi> denyed Chriſt, and <hi>Ionah,</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience told him he ſhould not be angry, when God asked him if he did well to be angry, <hi>Ionah</hi> 4.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A godly man may fall ſometimes into deliberate ſins againſt knowledge, when that which he knows habitually, he doth not actually think of; the violence of the temptation blinding the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and beating back the voice of Conſcience: ſo <hi>David</hi> is ſet forth (as a ſmarting ſpectacle of miſery, leſt any man ſhould ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as he did) to have fallen into the ſins of adultery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, againſt knowledge; <hi>Davids</hi> mind was ſo taken up with <hi>Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba,</hi> that he little thought of what he knew.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A godly man exceeding ſeldom or never falls into a delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſin againſt knowledge, when he doth actually and deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think, and judge of what he knows, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>But if ſinning againſt knowledge be ſo dangerous, is it not beſt to remain in ignorance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Ignorance, when it is againſt a mans Will, may excuſe from ſo much guilt, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. yet will it not excuſe wholly; <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. But when it is an ignorance of wicked diſpoſition, that a man is either willingly ignorant, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. or winks and cloſes up his eyes againſt the light, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.10, 11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.13, 14. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20. ſo that they will not read ſuch Books, nor hear ſuch Preachers, nor confer with ſuch men as might diſcover truth to them; God is wont not only Judicially to harden ſuch in their blindneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.14. compared with <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.40. but will alſo one day reckon with ſuch wilful ignorants, as if all their ſins had been committed againſt Knowledge.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Covenants principally conſiderable, which God made with his people?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beſides divers other Covenants which he made, as with <hi>Noah,</hi> and with every living creature, both fowl, and beaſt, that there ſhould be no more a flood to drown the Earth, of which Covenant he made the Rain-bow a token, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9, 9, 10, 11. as alſo a Covenant made with <hi>David,</hi> that his ſeed ſhould ſtill rule over <hi>Iſrael;</hi> with the <hi>Levites,</hi> that they ſhould be his Miniſters, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.20, 21, 25, 26. And a Covenant to give the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> to the Jews, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.9, 10. there are two other Covenants, moſt conſiderable.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41271:21"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which are they?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. A carnal typical Covenant, or Teſtament, called old, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. ſecond, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. worſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. which was dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the blood of beaſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.6, 7, 8. compared with <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.19. This was with all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the day when God took them by the hand to lead them out, of the Land of <hi>Egypt, Heb.</hi> 8.9. 2. A ſpiritual or new Covenant.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What did this old Covenant ſignifie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. An obligation of the Jews to the Moſaical Law in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.6, 7, 8. in the perfect obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, (it's thought) they were to have <hi>Canaan</hi> here, and Heaven hereafter; but failing in one point, they were under a curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. the Ceremonial part of it alſo ſhadowed our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was the proper effect of this old Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Bondage and ſlaviſh fear for not performing what this old Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant did require: this was ſignified by <hi>Hagar</hi> the bond-woman, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25. and this Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> in <hi>Arabia,</hi> a place without the bounds of the Land of promiſe, and by the fleſhly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was in bondage with her children; all three which reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances ſignifie, that the old Covenant begot children to bondage, not only under the unſupportable burthen of the Ceremonial Law, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. (which was a yoak of bondage, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. alſo <hi>chap.</hi> 5.1.) but alſo under the bondage of the curſe, and of Gods wrath, for not performing what the Law requires; for which cauſe the Law is ſaid to work wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. to be a miniſtration of death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7. and to ſlay the ſoul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.11. Now, as when a Pitcher falls upon the ſtones, it's the weakneſs of the Pitcher not, of the ſtones, that it is broken: So the reaſon why the Law miniſters death, is not becauſe of the weakneſs of the Law, but the weakneſs of our fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the other Covenant called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It's that Covenant which the Scripture cals the ſecond Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7. &amp; 9.1, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9. or the new Covenant, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13, &amp; 9.15. or the better Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. as being eſtabliſhed upon better Promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. of which Chriſt was ſurety, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is this new Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41271:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Gods free Promiſe, whereby he promiſeth, not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſins, and eternal life to them that are elect, or do believe the ſame; but alſo doth promiſe to to take away the ſtony heart, and to give them a new heart and a new ſpirit, and to put his Laws in their minds, and to write them in their hearts, ſo that all of them, from the leaſt to the greateſt know the Lord; yea, vouchſafes to be their God, and takes them to be his people.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Articles, or Branches in particular of this new Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are theſe: 1. Forgiveneſs of ſins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.12. <hi>I will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſs, and their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more.</hi> So that the Elect have not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from Original ſin, but from all tranſgreſſion under the firſt Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. by ſprinkling clean water upon them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26.25. Chriſts blood.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond branch is eternal life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. Chriſt is the Mediatour of the new Teſtament, that by the means of death (that is, of Chriſts death) they which are called might receive the promiſe of eternal inheritance: in this inheritance no bond-ſlave of Satan doth partake; which appears, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. in the type, in that the ſon of the Bond-woman, which was <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> did not partake with the ſon of the Free-woman, which was <hi>Iſaac;</hi> the meſſage from God being, <hi>Caſt out the Bond-woman and her ſon; for the ſon of the Bond-woman ſhall not be heir with the ſon of the Free-woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Branch is, <hi>ſoftning of the hearth, Ezek.</hi> 11.19. that whereas in the natural ſtate the heart was ſo hard, that neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, threat, nor command, mercy miſery moved; Now this ſtony heartedneſs is taken away, that the ſoul melts under the ſenſe of Chriſts ſufferings, it's own infirmities, and Gods mercies.</p>
               <p>The fourth Branch is, <hi>Newneſs</hi> whereby Chriſt doth not onely cleanſe the ſoul from all filthineſs in the reigne thereof, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12, 15. but alſo puts a new ſpirit, or a new frame of a Spirit within; which the Seripture calls <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> or <hi>change of minde, Rom.</hi> 12.2.</p>
               <p>The fifth Branch is, <hi>the putting of his laws in the hearts of the elect, Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11. ſo that they ſhall not teach every man his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41271:22"/> neighbour, or every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for all ſhall know the Lord from the leaſt to the greateſt; which is not meant of Notional knowledge (as if perſons in covenant with God ſtood in no need of being taught by Paſtors, parents, or neighbors) but of affective knowledge, that is, ſuch a knowledge as carries af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection with it, whereby they reliſh and ſavour good things. For this, ſee <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>John</hi> 6.45. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.9. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. this is ſuch a teaching as God teaches the Bees to work in their kind, whereby he puts an inſtinct in them ſo to work.</p>
               <p>The ſixth Branch is, <hi>the writing of his law in our hearts, Jer.</hi> 31.33. The pen wherewith he writes them, is his own Spirit, though the miniſtration be of men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. Now this writing is nothing but the inclination of the will to cloſe with Gods law in the bredth of it, the which branch <hi>Ezekiel</hi> expreſſeth thus, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>I will cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes, and you ſhall keep my judgements:</hi> ſo that whereas in the natural ſtate there was an enmity betwixt the heart and the law, the Spirit ſo bends the will, that the heart and the law become ſutable, anſwering one another, as the Seal and the Wax.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Branch is, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people:</hi> whereby God promiſeth to communicate to us not only every good thing, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 84.1.2. but alſo himſelf, and that we that were enemies and ſtrangers, ſhall be his people, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.25.26. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who was the Mediator of this new Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. Firſt, the promiſes were made to <hi>Abrahams ſeed,</hi> not <hi>Seeds,</hi> but <hi>Seed; one Seed,</hi> which was Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.15, 16. And by vertue of our union with Chriſt, we come to be heirs according to promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. the promiſes being firſt inſtated upon Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. as being heir of all things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are the perſons that have benefit by this new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> All the elect from the beginning to the end of the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. In the times of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there were many children of the new Covenant: and though <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> chap. 31.31. call it <hi>a new Covenant,</hi> yet doth he ſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41271:23"/> call it, becauſe it was clearly manifeſted by the Apoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But how can the Covenant be made with all the elect, ſeeing ſundry of them are not capable of divers branches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as infants, idiots?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> You muſt remember, that the new Covenant is called a Teſtament, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28.) or a Will: Now an Infant is capable of a Legacy. 2. Though they are not capable of all the Branches of the Covenant, yet are they of ſome, as forgiveneſs of ſins, and eternal life; by theſe they are ſaved, though they have not the other.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How doth it appear the new Covenant was alſo a Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe as other Wills and Teſtaments are, it was confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the death of the Teſtator, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16. This was eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the blood of Chriſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. Beſides, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, properly ſignifies a Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What difference betwixt the two Covenants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The old Covenant required perfect obedience, but gave no ſtrength to do it: hence called <hi>[Faulty] Heb.</hi> 8.7. not in reſpect of it ſelf, but us; faulty with a faultineſs of imperfection, not of ſinfulneſs: but in the new Covenant is a promiſe of ability to do what God requires: As he requires love of us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. ſo he promiſes it; ſo doth he for faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. repentance, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. and Gods fear, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.40. Hence called a <hi>Covenant of Grace,</hi> becauſe he doth our part as well as his own.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the old Covenant required obedience in the rigor, and curſt the tranſgreſſor for every breach, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. the new Covenant requires on the creatures part onely the perfection of ſincerity, which conſiſts principally in an univerſal purpoſe and endeavour for new obedience, <hi>John</hi> 15.14. with an hearty ſorrow if they be overtaken contrary to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the old Covenant was much upon temporal promiſes, as <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.3. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1, 17. but the new Covenant runs upon ſpiritual and eternal promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the old Covenant is aboliſhed and come to an end, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Caſt out the Bond-woman and her ſon, Gal.</hi> 4.30.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41271:23"/> But the new Covenant is everlaſting, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.20. in oppoſition to the abrogated covenant, ſo that as a wife is free from her husband when he is dead, ſo we are freed from the old Covenant, it being dead; and we being new married unto Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1, 2 3 4.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the old Covenant was very dark, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Moſes</hi> put a veil over his face, to ſignifie the children of Iſrael could not ſee Chriſt. Hence, as thoſe that learn the Rudiments or beginning of a language, are in bondage not knowing what benefit will come by them: ſo were ſundry Jews and others under the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Rudiments of the world, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9. and could not with any clearneſs underſtand it. Contrary, the new Teſtament is clear; the Miniſters of it uſe great plainneſs of ſpeech, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12, 13. and the children of the new Covenant ſee with much plainneſs, as in a looking-glaſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>But ſeeing you ſay the old Covenant is aboliſhed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no are we freed from the Law of</hi> Moſes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Believers are delivered, Firſt, from the curſe for breach of it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. Secondly, from the covenant of the Law, under which notion it ſeems to have been delivered on Mount <hi>Sinai, Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6.8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8. Thirdly, from the hand-writing of the Law, as it teſtified againſt us our guilt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. as a free Creditor not onely forgives the debt, but alſo cancels the bond that might witneſs it againſt his debtor. Fourthly, from the power it hath to ſtir up to ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5, 8. the more the Law forbids ſin to natural men, with much more proneneſs they are carried to it. Fifthly, from the <hi>Moſaical</hi> inſtitution of it, as it was by <hi>Moſes</hi> peculiarly appointed to the <hi>Jews, Iohn</hi> 7.19. <hi>Did not</hi> Moſs <hi>give [You] the Law?</hi> John 15.25. <hi>It is written in [Their] law.</hi> And elſe why did <hi>Moſes</hi> command the ſeventh day from the creation to be obſerved, and we obſerve the firſt day of the week?</p>
               <p>Q <hi>How are we bound to obſerve</hi> Moſes <hi>his Lawes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. As they are Laws of Nature: I call thoſe laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which men by the light of nature practice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. as that God is to be worſhipped parents honoured, that no man is to take away the Wife or goods of another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. So far as they are Laws of equity and juſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So far as they are Laws of holineſs; for the Children of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41271:24"/> new Teſtament who lived under the old Teſtament, made great conſcience of them, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. and they tend to the perfecting of the new Creature, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. Hence the Spirit writes the Law in regenerate mens hearts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. which he would not do if it were not a rule of holineſs; yea, all Gods Law is holy, juſt, and good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. whereunto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate men, (as ſuch) had reſpect, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. yea are bound to have reſpect, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.10, 11. all which proves the holineſs of Gods Law, I mean the Scriptures pen'd by <hi>Moſes,</hi> with all other prophetical Scriptures which expound the ſame.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What comfort may we draw from this new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Much comfort: when thy luſts are prevailing, God will ſprinkle clean water, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. when hardneſs of heart aſſaults, God will take away a ſtony heart, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. when old luſts aſſaile, that God will give a new heart, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. ſo when thy heart begins to diſrelliſh good things, that God will give thee a ſavory heart to reliſh them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.11. if thy heart riſe up againſt any of Gods Commands, that God will write this Law in thy heart, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. and when thy heart ſhall doubt of Gods favor, remember that he ſaith, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people,</hi> Heb. 8.10.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What are the ſigns of the new Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two: 1. Baptiſme, 2. The Supper of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Declare in particular what Baptiſm is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſigne of my fellowſhip with Chriſt in his death, buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and reſurrection, that as my body is waſhed and buried in water, ſo I believe my ſins are waſhed away, and buried in the death of the Lord Jeſus; and as I did riſe againe out of the water, ſo I did riſe againe with Chriſt, being diſcharged from my ſins in his death and reſurrection; and have already begun and profeſſed that I am bound to riſe to walk with Chriſt in newneſs of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5, 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are the right ſubjects of Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe that are made Diſciples or Scholars of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. that make profeſſion of believing with their whole hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22, 23. and of their repentance from dead
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41271:24"/> works, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. and of their right knowledge of the object of worſhip, that is, the Trinity, into whoſe Name they are baptized, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. and of their natural corruptions; without which, they will ſee no need of waſhing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.14. and of their ſelf-denial; without which, they are not Chriſts Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. and ſo not to be baptized, by the very words of the Commiſſion of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Make diſciples all Nations, baptizing them;</hi> for the Greek word ſignifies <hi>to make diſciples,</hi> and not barely <hi>to teach.</hi>) Alſo, they muſt make profeſſion of their ſpiritual life; without which, they are not members of Chriſt the living head; alſo, of the reſurrection of the body, which is alſo ſignified in Baptiſme, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. and of the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not infants be baptized?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, in no wiſe; it being groſs will-worſhip, condemned, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.9. the Scripture declaring baptiſme to be applyed onely to thoſe that are diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. and believe, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12, 37. &amp; 18, 8. and repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.39. and have <hi>put on Chriſt, Gal.</hi> 3.27. and have received the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.41. We muſt not preſume to apply it to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Beſides, infants underſtand not the new Covenant, therefore they have nothing to do with the ſignes thereof, unleſs God had commanded otherwiſe: neither are they in Chriſts commiſſion, and therefore excluded to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not the command of circumciſion to the Jews, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Chriſtian parents to baptize infants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If you make the command of Circumciſion to be the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or command for infants baptiſme, you hold forth Circumciſion ſtill, and ſo hold forth that which typifies Chriſt to come in the fleſh. Perſons were circumciſed upon a fleſhly covenant intailed to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, not to regeneration: but now believers are baptized upon a command of God, as a declaration of the waſhing away of their ſins in Chriſts blood, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.16. Circumciſion, with the reſt of the ceremonies, were aboliſhed in Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9, 10, 1. If we may call back one, we may call back all. To ſay, So for a command bindes us and ſo far not without a plaine declaration of Gods will, is high preſumption. We are therefore to <hi>ſtand faſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41271:25"/> in our liberty, Gal.</hi> 2.16, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10 11. &amp; 5.1, 2, 3. The Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10 11, 12. to take the Jewiſh brethren wholly off from Circumciſion, doth not ſay, We have another ordinance in ſtead of circumciſion, or by vertue of that command; but, We have Chriſt in ſtead of all; we are circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands, by the Spirit of Chriſt; <hi>we are compleat in him,</hi> verſe 11. not with a compleatneſs of outward ordinances, but by a compleatneſs of Chriſt alone. It is ſuppoſed by ſome, that without a ſucceſſion of ſome ordinance inſtead of Circumciſion, we are not compleat in Chriſt, or not ſo compleat as the Jews; but this is, 1. Falſe, becauſe it's contrary to that the Apoſtle aſſerts, that we are <hi>compleat in Chriſt</hi> alone, becauſe in him is the fulneſs of all that was ſhadowed. 2. It is dangerous, becauſe the ſame reaſon that will conclude we are not compleat without a ſucceſſion of ſome ordinances in ſtead of Circumciſion, will conclude we are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat without a ſucceſſion of ſomething inſtead of Temple, Sacrifices, Altar; and ſo, after the Popiſh manner, all Jewiſh Rites will be recalled, under new names. The queſtion ſtarted at <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> was, not univerſally, wherein a Chriſtians perfection conſiſted; but wherein it conſiſted in point of Juſtification; whether by Chriſt alone, or by the law and circumciſion joyned with him. To this he ſaith, <hi>We are compleat in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But may I not draw a proportion, that as infants in the time of the Jews were circumciſed, ſo infants of believers under the times of the Goſpel may be baptized?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In no wiſe. We muſt not make additions in worſhip from our conceited proportions. Proportions of Gods making may be obſerved, as theſe following: <hi>The Prieſts lips muſt preſerve knowledge, Mal.</hi> 2.7. ſo muſt <hi>the Biſhops be apt to teach,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. As the Prieſts by offering ſacrifice held forth Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. ſo the Miniſters by preaching, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. as the Prieſt was to have a Conſecration, ſo the Miniſters an Ordination: Will it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that a command to a Prieſt to offer a ſacrifice propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atory, ſhould be a command to a Goſpell-Miniſter to offer a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice propitiatory, as the Maſs-prieſts do? Or a command for a Prieſt to weat a linen Ephod, ſhould be a command to a Miniſter to wear a Surplice? or that there muſt be a Pope over the Church, becauſe there was an high-prieſt in time of the law? or that we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:41271:25"/> muſt receive the Supper with unleavened bread, becauſe the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over was ſo received? Yet do theſe as well follow, as baptizing of infants, from circumciſion of infants.</p>
               <p>The true proportions flowing hence, are theſe: 1. none were circumciſed, but thoſe commanded or exemplified; ſo none ought to be baptized but ſuch. 2. As <hi>Abraham</hi> believing was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and all the males of his houſe, both men, and children of eight dayes old; both bond and free: ſo now any man believing muſt be baptized, with all his houſhold, both men and male-chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of eight dayes old, both bond and free. The formal reaſon why <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Jews received Circumciſion, was Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand concerning infants baptiſme: if any ſuch command be, let it be produced.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Whether are the children of believers in covenant toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their parents?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: for the children are oft out of covenant, when the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is in covenant. It's ſaid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7, 9. that <hi>they that are of the faith of</hi> Abraham, <hi>are the children of</hi> Abraham; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where hath God made a promiſe to be a God of believers and their ſeed, unleſs upon a preſuppoſal that the Lord ſhall call the ſeed as well as the father <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. If the natural poſterity of <hi>Abraham</hi> were not in the covenant of grace by vertue of that promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. as appears, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7. neither becauſe they are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> are they all children; and <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>Theſe that are the children of the fleſh, theſe are not the children of God; but the children of the promiſe are counted for the ſeed:</hi> much leſs are the children of other believers children of promiſe by vertue of generation.</p>
               <p>He that ſhall hear men preach, that children of believers are in the covenant of grace, and they that are in the covenant of grace cannot fall away, may be apt to conceive himſelf in that covenant of grace without repentance and faith, and ſhall be ſaved without any obedience. And may not, on the other ſide, godly parents, when they ſee their children live vitiouſly, doubt whether they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be true believers, becauſe they ſee not their children in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace?</p>
               <p>There is a promiſe or calling home the natural ſeed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Rom.</hi> 11.27. but God hath not made any ſuch promiſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41271:26"/> to any, much leſs to all the natural ſeed of any believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>Are not the ordinances the outward part of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? and is not the title to this hereditary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Is a box that conveyes a Jewel, the outward part of the Jewel? Is a conduit-pipe that conveyes water, the outward part of the water? is <hi>Aaron</hi>'s pot the outward part of the Manna that it kept?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the ordinances were the outward part of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, how is title hereto hereditary, ſeeing that not only from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, but even whole Churches, as <hi>Epheſus,</hi> &amp;c. theſe ordinances have been removed long ſince.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it is nowhere ſaid in Scripture, The childe ſhall be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by vertue of his beliving fathers being baptized; or enjoy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances becauſe his father enjoyed them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is but one covenant now, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11. the articles and branches whereof are inward, and ſo is the ſeal thereof, the Spirit, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.13. There can be no ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ward diſpenſation of an uncertain thing: now it is uncertain of any individual infant, whether he be in the new covenant.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But doth not Chriſt ſay.</hi> Of little children is the Kingdome of God? <hi>therefore they may be baptized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. There's two wayes of belonging to Gods Kingdome. 1. By way of election; which is ſecret. 2. By calling; which is manifeſt. The Ordinance of Baptiſm ought not to be diſpenſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on election, or remiſſion of ſins, which is ſecret; but upon the manifeſtation thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt baptized not, onely <hi>laid on his hands on them, John</hi> 4.2. Had Chriſt uſed to baptize infants, the diſciples would not have kept them back.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Kingdome of God being taken for the Kingdome of grace, the Kingdome of glory, and the viſible Church it would poſe any man living to prove that the viſible Church ſhould be meant here.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Beſides, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.16. they were not infants, becauſe Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>call</hi> them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What further reaſons have you againſt infant-bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:41271:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The baptiſme of Chriſt is a burial in waters; the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of infants is a ſprinkling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3 4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Baptiſme doth not cauſally effectively or actively; I mean, it doth not, from the work done, confer faith; but refers to the new covenant, in by, and through the unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtanding; therefore where it is diſpenſed, there ought to be an underſtanding to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſame benefit confirmed in the Supper that this, remiſſion of ſins, is confirmed in baptiſme; therefore infants being excluded from the one, for want of examination, they are alſo excluded from the other, for want of faith and repentance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Infant-baptiſme hinders baptiſme from being diſpenſed as <hi>John</hi> and other Apoſtles diſpenſed it: they diſpenſed it upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith; but no ſuch thing can be in infants.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>In what manner muſt baptiſme be adminiſtred?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſubject muſt be right; that is, not onely taught, but taught ſo long that he be made a diſciple, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not by ſprinkling, but by burying, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. not of the brow or face onely, but of the whole body, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. in <hi>much water,</hi> Joh. 3.23. into which the baptizer and the perſon to be baptized are to enter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. who is to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into the name of Father, Son, and Spirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. in token of remiſſion of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. the name of God being firſt called upon, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Do you judge it better to defer baptiſme till perſons be able to make profeſſion of their faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes. Infants cannot give any ground to any diſpenſer of baptiſme why he ſhould diſpence it to them. The diſpencing it to infants, confounds the world and the Church together; many hereby being made Chriſtians in name who never made choice of Chriſt nor have any love to Chriſtianity: yea hereby the Churches are filled with rotten members; many of which growing up, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the true members.</p>
               <p>By deferring baptiſme till perſons know Chriſt, the Churches would in time come to have a right matter.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Have not infants faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. No: they have not reaſon to diſcern good or evil <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.39. <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.11. had they faith, they were preſently to be admitted to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41271:27"/> the Supper: faith is an act of the Underſtanding as well as of the Will.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether is there any reaſon that Baptiſme ſhould ſucceed circumciſion, becauſe that as circumciſion ſigned the ſpiritual part of the covenant that is, circumciſion of heart; ſo baptiſme ſhould ſignifie the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. No: for the Manna, the water flowing out of the rock, the ſacrifices under the law, and the ſprinkling of blood, ſignified the ſame; yet will not any man ſay baptiſme ſucceeded theſe, becauſe of the ſignification.</p>
               <p>The Lords Supper ſignified the ſame; yet will no man ſay the Lords Supper ſucceeds Circumciſion in reſpect of any uſe: In no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, that I know of, is there a likeneſs betwixt Circumciſion and Baptiſme; and therefore to draw infants baptiſme from it, is no conſequence. And ſo much more, becauſe the ſtate of the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church is at an end, which was national; and we have Goſpel-congregational-Churches.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Circumciſion was a ſeal of</hi> Abrahams <hi>faith; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baptiſme coming in the room of it, ought to be diſpenſed to infants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. Then none ſhould be baptized, ſave thoſe which have faith and the righteouſneſs of faith. Infants, though they may have a righteouſneſs, yet they cannot have the righteouſneſs of faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have no power to believe. If there were any ſuch ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion then baptiſm ſhould ſeal the righteouſneſs in faith; which it cannot in infants.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is abſurd that baptiſme ſhould ſucceed Circumciſion, in reſpect of infancy, not mentioned in the text; and not in growth of ſtature, which now <hi>Abraham</hi> had; nor in qualification of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of faith, which was the qualification of <hi>Abraham:</hi> both which are mentioned in the text.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Baptiſme ſucceeds circumciſion, neither, 1. In reſpect of ſubject: ſome there were to be circumciſed, that are not to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; as bought ſervants: and ſome to be baptized, that were not to be circumciſed; as females. 2. Nor in reſpect of ſociety: Circumciſion was an inlet into the Jewiſh Church, Baptiſm into the Chriſtian Church. 3. Nor in reſpect of uſe: for Circumciſion en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged Jews and Proſelytes to the Jewiſh ceremonies; but Baptiſme is a declarative of remiſſion of ſins.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41271:27"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who hath the power of diſpenſing the ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. It ſeems to me, that, 1. Apoſtles, 2. Evangeliſts or Goſpel-preachers, have power herein.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How prove you that there is any ſuch Office in the Church as Apoſtles or Meſſengers? for an Apoſtle is nothing but a Meſſenger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. Becauſe as God gave Paſtors and Teachers, ſo did he give Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints, Eph</hi> 4.10, 11, 12, 13. therefore, it follows, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat, <hi>Till all the Saints be perfected, till the body of Chriſt be built up,</hi> this office is to remaine in the Church. To diſtinguiſh, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers are ordinary officers, but the Office of Apoſtles and Evangeliſts is extraordinary; or that the work of perfecting Saints and edifying Chriſts body lyes upon Paſtors and Teachers, and not upon Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, is to put a diſtinction where the Scripture puts none: the twelve Apoſtles were given, before Chriſt his aſcenſion; but theſe Apoſtles, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. were given after: ſee <hi>verſe</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, it appears from Gods own order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church, firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, thirdly teachers.</hi> If he ſet them firſt, what are we, that we can either aboliſh them, or ſet them in other places when God will give them?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, we finde (2) Apoſtles in ſundry of the Churches, therefore they are a ſtanding Office: At <hi>Epheſus, Eph.</hi> 4.10. at <hi>Philippi, Phil.</hi> 2.25. the <hi>Greek</hi> word is <hi>Apoſtolos:</hi> At <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 13.23. at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 1.26. at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. See alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23. <hi>or our brethren be enquired of, they are the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of the Churches.</hi> So in the <hi>Greeke, Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul an Apoſtle, not of men, nor by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> to ſhew there were Apoſtles by men, or of mens ſending, beſides thoſe ſent by Chriſt. <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junia</hi> were Apoſtles in <hi>Rome,</hi> or thereabouts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. they were of note among the Apoſtles, not onely becauſe they were of eſteem, but becauſe they did labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly preach: ſo were <hi>Barnabas, Silas, Timotheus, Luke, Mark,</hi> &amp;c. though none of the twelve.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41271:28"/>
               <p>Fourthly, Apoſtles are called to rejoyce at <hi>Babylons</hi> deſtruction, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20. Now if there were no Apoſtles but the firſt twelve, <hi>Babylon</hi> could do them no wrong, ſeeing ſhe was not in being till three hundred years after Chriſt: therefore ſome Apoſtles muſt be meant, to whom <hi>Babylon</hi> had done miſchief.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, it appears from Reaſon; there is as much need of Apoſtles for to gather perſons from their natural and Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh eſtate, as there was to gather them from Judaiſme and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſme.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is eſſential to an Apoſtle in theſe times?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Abilities of grace and parts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Secondly the choice and ſending forth of a Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.19. the Meſſengers that went along with <hi>Paul, verſe</hi> 23. are ſaid to <hi>be choſen of the Church; Barnabas</hi> was ſent by the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to go to <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 11.22. <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> was thus ſent by the Church at <hi>Philippi, Phil.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Paul</hi> by the Church of <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 13.2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the office of ſuch an Apoſtle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. To bring the Doctrine of ſalvation, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.22. &amp; 13.26 &amp; 28.28.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to baptize, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to lay on hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.5 6 7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. after Baptiſme.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ordination of Elders and Deacons, and to lay hands on them, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. yea, he is to have a great hand in Church cenſures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>Q <hi>What is the difference betwixt the twelve Apoſtles called immediately of Chriſt, and thoſe called mediately of Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The twelve or at leaſt eleven, were called perſonally of Chriſt; the Apoſtles of Churches are called virtually by Chriſt his command, or order, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſ.</hi> 4.10. He that can immediately make out his call, hath enough to ſatisfie his own and other mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though not called perſonally by Chriſt. Some of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles called by Chriſt perſonally, were pen-men of Scripture, and ſo were infallible 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. yet were they not infallible in every thing <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.13. but had they ſo been, yet is ſending of a Church and giftedneſs the formal cauſe of Apoſtleſhip, as was proved before, and not infallibility.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41271:28"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>But were not miracles the ſignes of an Apoſtle?</hi> 2 Cor. 12.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: The Apoſtle ſaith not, wonders of miracles were ſigns of an Apoſtle, (which many other believers could do) but he ſaith, the ſigns of an Apoſtle (which was converſion of ſouls, called <hi>the ſeal of his Apoſtleſhip,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2.) were wrought by him in ſignes and wonders.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Is not this Doctrine concerning Apoſtles, ſet down very barely in Scripture?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Doctrine concerning Apoſtles, comparing it with the Doctrine of the Reſurrection and laſt Judgement, is not ſet down with ſuch clearneſs; but comparing it with the Aſſertions about the calling of Paſtors and Elders, as now practiſed in the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches (as they are called) there is greatneſs of light: for the call of the Miniſters goes upon one of theſe three heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Succeſſion of perſons:</hi> as that the Miniſters have been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by them who have been ordained of others. Now this is moſt uncertain, having been interrupted ſo often, and yet once were enough to make it a nullity. Beſides, that having been no Scripture writ for above this fifteen hundred yeers, all that men can have for it is onely humane teſtimony, which is no ground to him that ſcruples, <hi>By what power and authority do you this?</hi> Beſides, all ſucceſſion hath gone through the filthy chapel of the <hi>Romiſh Churches,</hi> which have been for many hundred years over-ſpread with Idolatry, will-worſhip, and falſe matter; wherein the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers reſpectively, in whom ſucceſſive power is ſuppoſed to reſide, were the chiefeſt ſticklers, and deeplieſt guilty in thoſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Proportion;</hi> that becauſe the Church choſe an Apoſtle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church may now chuſe a Paſtor; becauſe that the Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ordained Elders in every Church, which they had been inſtrument<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l to bring to the faith <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. therefore a Company of Synod-men or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esbyters may ordaine in every Church; or becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete</hi> to ordain Elders in every City <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. therefore other men may be deputed to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine by the power of a national or provincial Priesbytery: if then affirmations for the one be dark, how much more dark is the other?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41271:29"/>3. <hi>Radicality,</hi> that is, that though all Officers and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are loſt, yet that the power reſolves it ſelf into the Church, as the ſap of trees in winter goes into the root; and that the power of recovering Officers being there ſeated, any Church or Company of Believers hath authority from Chriſt to bring this power into act: which being the beſt ground that I know the reformed Churches to have from theſe Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10, 11, 12. do thereupon in ſundry independent Churches chuſe and ordain Officers of Paſtor, Teacher, Deacon, Elder; and why not alſo may they chuſe Apoſtle and Evangeliſt, or Meſſenger and Goſpel-Preacher, being there is the ſame radical power for the one that there is for the other?</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who beſides Apoſtles have power to baptize?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Evangeliſts or Goſpel-Preachers: ſo <hi>Philip</hi> baptized the Eunuch, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. and many of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> verſ. 12. now by Goſpel-Preachers, I mean thoſe who though not ſent by a Church, yet being gifted ſhall preach ſoul-ſavingly, whether ſent of the Magiſtrate when Churches are either defective or unable, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.7 8. or going of their own accord, as thoſe who went out, <hi>John</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> verſ. 6, 7. ſuch an one was <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. on whom hands were laid, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. the difference betwixt theſe Goſpel-Preachers and Apoſtles, ſeems to be this, that as the Apoſtles were ſent into the world to convert perſons to the faith, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. ſo theſe Evangeliſts went unto the Churches to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the work the Apoſtles had begun: ſuch were <hi>Titus, Mark, Tychicus, Epaphras:</hi> yet were not Apoſtles limited onely to the World, nor Evangeliſts to the Churches.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether may not other diſciples baptize?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Scripture doth not ſo clearly ſet down herein yet it is more then probable that <hi>Ananias,</hi> a Diſciple of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> baptized <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9.17, 18. and that the three Brethren that came along with <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>Joppa,</hi> baptized <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Company, <hi>Acts</hi> 10 48.</p>
               <p>Beſides, ordinary Diſciples may make Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.21, 22. therefore they may baptize, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. if we ſay the eleven Diſciples onely were appointed by the Commiſſion to make Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, then it follows, that the Brethren that made ſo many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples at <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſhould have ſinned in their ſo doing, for want
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41271:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> of a Commiſſion. Yet may not women baptize, becauſe they are forbid to teach, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But is not baptizedneſs in the diſpenſer of Baptiſme, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Baptiſme, ſeeing we never read any unbaptized perſon did baptize?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Baptizedneſs in the diſpenſer is not eſſential to Baptiſme: for then, 1. an Ordinance of God ſhould be adminiſtred upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Teſtimony; for how can any man be ſure that there hath been a line of baptized Perſons from the Apoſtles to him that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized thee, eſpecially ſeeing no Scripture hath been given by God for this fifteen yeers and upwards?</p>
               <p>Beſides <hi>John</hi> who baptized firſt, we read nothing of his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, beſides none of thoſe that were baptized in Scripture; as the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> the three thouſand, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.2. <hi>Lydia,</hi> the Jaylor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> never asked any of the diſpenſers of Baptiſme (though ſtrangers to them) whether themſelves were baptized; which had been moſt material, had a diſpenſers baptizedneſs been eſſential to Baptiſme; eſpecially, they living among the Scribes and Phariſees, who were ready to queſtion by what Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity do you theſe things?</p>
               <p>Beſides, were baptizedneſs thus eſſential to Baptiſme, then the Commiſſion would have run; Let a baptized perſon make Diſciples all Nations; but its otherwiſe, make Diſciples all Nations.</p>
               <p>Beſides, there ſhould be a continual uncertainties, in reſpect of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm upon the conſciences of all Chriſtians; ſeeing they could never be certain of a line of Baptizers: eſpecially, after two or three removes, and ſo ſtill ſhould they be uncertain of their own Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Beſides, an unbaptized perſon may clearly hold forth the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, and ſo Make ſouls Diſciples; what ſhould hinder them but that he may tender the ſigne thereof to thoſe parties that lay hold on that Covenant?</p>
               <p>Beſides, this would prove Baptiſme not to be of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. becauſe it comes to nought, for want of the knowledge of baptized<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the diſpenſer.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether is the doing of miracles eſſential to a diſpenſer of Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: 1. <hi>John</hi> the firſt diſpenſer did no miracle, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.41. Now an Ordinance when it is firſt inſtituted or diſpenſed, the diſpenſer did bring it in with all the eſſentials.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41271:30"/>2. Then ſhould the diſpenſers of Baptiſme alwayes have wrought miracles before they adminiſtred Baptiſme, in the ſight of the perſon to be baptized, ſeeing perſons to be baptized ought to partake of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing eſſential to Baptiſm; but the Scriptures mention no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle that <hi>Philip</hi> did when he baptized the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> nor when <hi>John</hi> baptized in <hi>Jordan,</hi> or when <hi>Lydia</hi> was baptized.</p>
               <p>Beſides; if the eſſence of Baptiſme conſiſted in the diſpenſers do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a miracle, then there is no true Baptiſme in the world, becauſe no miracle hath been done this thirteen hundred yeers, <hi>Chryſoſt. Hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in</hi> 2 Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, miracles are not much uſeful to a perſon that is preſently to be baptized, ſeeing he is deemed a Believer already; but they are of uſe to unconverted perſons, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, miracles alone cannot confirm any one Ordinance, becauſe falſe prophets may do them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. &amp; 24.24. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. from all which it follows, Miracle-working is not eſſential to a diſpenſer of baptiſme,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Impoſition, or laying on of Hands.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>HOw many ſorts of laying on of hands do you finde in the New Teſtament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Beſides occaſional laying on of hands, as on little children, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.15. and miraculous, when the Apoſtles laid their hands on the ſick, and they recovered, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 28.8. there ore two uſual laying on of hands.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in ordination of Officers, which is the pointing out of the perſon choſe to an office in the Church, whom the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to God in prayer. This is acknowledged by all.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there is a laying on of hands after baptiſm, which is a praying for an increaſe of the Spirit on baptized perſons, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether is laying on of hands after baptiſm, an ordinance of force, obliging Chriſtians in theſe times?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Reſerving others of Gods ſervants to their light who think
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41271:30"/> otherwiſe, and acknowledging a dark revelation of this in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of other Fundamentals, and profeſſing ingenuouſly I could not ſuffer ſo much in the witneſs of this point, as I could in plainer points and Articles, as of thoſe concerning the fall of man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by Chriſt, the reſurrection, and the laſt judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and declaring that though Teachers may not teach, nor people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any thing which hath not ſome footing in the word of God, yet may they ſpeak of things which they know but weakly: Theſe things being premiſed, I ſhall acknowledge laying on of hands on baptized perſons after baptiſme, to be an Apoſtolical inſtitution, or an Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What grounds have you to prove laying on of hands after Baptiſme, to be an Apoſtolical inſtitution?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Theſe: Firſt, becauſe the Apoſtle makes it one of the ſix principles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. or word of the beginning of Chriſt, as in the <hi>Greek;</hi> nay, he makes it a foundation-point as well as Repentance, Faith, Baptiſme, Reſurrection, and laſt Judgement. Now theſe being Fundamentals, wherein all converted perſons are to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical in the belief, how can impoſition of hands be excluded from being ſo received? It is abſurd to think that one of theſe ſix prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſhould ceaſe in a ſhort time, and the other five to remaine till the end of the world; and yet the Apoſtle calls them all by the name of a <hi>Foundation,</hi> and places it betwixt Faith and Repentance, the Reſurrection and the laſt Judgement, ſo that there is no coming to ſlight it, it being fenced on every ſide.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing we acknowledge a laying on of hands in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, do we not acknowledge theſe ſix principles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No reaſon can be brought why laying on of hands in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſhould be from this Text acknowledged, and the other after Baptiſme on baptized perſons, excluded. Nay, it ſeemeth, that laying on of hands on baptized perſons, ſhould be primarily meant, becauſe the Apoſtle ſeemeth to couple theſe foundation-Principles, ſo that as faith and Repentance go together, and the Reſurrection and laſt Judgement; ſo Baptiſm and Impoſition of go together.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But whether is there my command for laying on of hands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is as much commandment for laying on of hands on
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41271:31"/> baptized perſons after Baptiſme, as on perſons ordained to Office: for both of them we finde Apoſtolical practice.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Apoſtle calling it a foundation that was firſt laid, as appears in theſe words <hi>[Not laying again the Foundation]</hi> hath a virtual command in it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other ground have you for laying on of hands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> We have the practice of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.14, 15, 16, 17. The Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> laid their hands on thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> whom <hi>Philip</hi> had baptized, as <hi>verſe</hi> 17. <hi>Then laid they their hands on them:</hi> The Antecedent to this Pronoune Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative <hi>Them,</hi> could be no other then the baptized <hi>Samaritans.</hi> See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>But in theſe examples there were viſible gifts given; but there is not ſo in yours in theſe times: therefore your lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands is not the ſame with theirs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe viſible gifts given, were no parts of the Ordinance, much leſs eſſentialities, but onely the crowns and ornaments of it; God hereby confirming the truth of that doctrine, and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that perſon into whoſe name they were baptized.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is a miſtake to think that alwayes when the Apoſtles laid on hands, viſible gifts were given: for <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands on <hi>Timothy,</hi> and God conveyed nothing therein, ſave inward gifts and graces, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Stir up the gift which was given thee by the laying on of the hands of me.</hi> So in the <hi>Greek.</hi> If any man ſay theſe gifts were conveyed on <hi>Timothy</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> in ordination, and not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Baptiſm, <hi>A.</hi> The contrary appears, becauſe the gift given <hi>Timothy</hi> in ordination, was by the hands of all the Elderſhip, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 14.14. but this gift was given in laying on of hands by <hi>Paul</hi> alone: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laying on of hands after Baptiſme is meant in this place.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But if laying on of hands after Baptiſme be an ordinance of Chriſt, what is conveyed in it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An increaſe of the Spirit, ſo that as the Spirit is conveyed in the uſe of prayer, and preaching, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. and Baptiſme, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. and the Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. ſo alſo is an increaſe of the Spirit conveyed in laying no of hands, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Stir up the gift which is in thee, which was given thee by the laying on of my hands.</hi> See, he had the gift or grace of God in him before, and now in laying on of <hi>Pauls</hi> hands, it was increaſed; yet is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41271:31"/> not laying on of hands the onely or principal part of this Ordinance, but praiſe is the principal part; in the uſe whereof the other being adjoyned, theſe fore-named Gifts and Graces of the Spirit are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed. I take it to be <hi>vehiculum ſpiritus,</hi> or a channel to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the increaſes of the ſpirit to believing hearts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But what promiſe is there that there ſhall be an increaſe of the Spirit given in laying on of hands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. A Command is enough to receive an Ordinance, though there were no promiſe annexed concerning any benefit; and we have proved a virtual Command out of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What promiſe there is of laying on of hands by the Elders, the ſame is here; yet is it acknowledged by all, that the Spirit is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed in the increaſes in the Elders laying on of hands.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Example of the conveyance of the Spirit into the Samaritans, and into <hi>Timothy</hi> his heart in the laying on of hands, is an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging ground for baptized perſons to ſubmit thereto, and expect the like benefit.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is a promiſe of the increaſe of the Spirit to the prayer of Faith, whenever poured out, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.13. and why not to the prayer of Faith, when now poured out? now the promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt being made to all baptized ones, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38 39. ſuch may well pray in faith for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But whether are theſe promiſes bound to the laying on of hands, ſo that then when hands are laid on, and by that means, the Gifts and Graces of the Spirit are conveyed, when the Churches, Apoſtle, or Apoſtles lay on their hands: we muſt not invent a meanes through which promiſes muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. The promiſe is bound to the prayer of faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That not onely in, but by laying on of hands, the Spirit is conveyed, appears, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No man can ſay, that either Baptiſme, Supper, or impoſition of hands apply the promiſe; it is the Spirit and Faith alone that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the promiſe; yet is laying on of hands ſuch a means as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calls a foundation, and a means through which both on Gods behalf and our behalf, the promiſe may be applyed, becauſe we read Believers to have received the promiſe herein; we ſay not of laying on of hands that, it is a means through which the promiſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41271:32"/> muſt be, God being a free Agent) but a means through which the promiſe may be, and hath been conveyed into the ſoul, as in <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> his caſe appears.</p>
               <p>Leſt any man think this a new Doctrine, let him conſult the Fathers, who oft mention laying on of hands after Baptiſme. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. de Baptiſmo, Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt. ad Inbaianum.</hi> Alſo his Epiſtle <hi>ad Stephanum. Tertul. lib. de reſurrect. Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Cont. Donatiſtas, &amp; Cont. literas Petilliani. Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiades ad Epiſc. Hiſpan. Fabianus Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Epiſcop. Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Ambroſ. de his qui Myſter. initiantur. cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de ſacramento, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt. ad omnes Orthodox. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, Conſtit. Apoſtol. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>Euſeb. Hiſtor. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 35. with others: and <hi>Eſtius in Heb.</hi> 6.1. ſaith, that all antiquity teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth laying on of hands after Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing the Apoſtles who laid on hands after Baptiſm, were ſuch Apoſtles as were immediately called of Chriſt, as</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.17, <hi>and</hi> Paul, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>how will it hold from them to the Apoſtles of the Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Very well: For firſt, Apoſtles of the Churches, though they have not an immediate call from Chriſt perſonally on earth, yet they have a call from him vertually, in that ſince his aſcenſion into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>He gave ſome to be Apoſtles,</hi> Eph. 4.12. <hi>for the work of the Miniſtery,</hi> that is, to do what belonged to their office. What difference betwixt perſons called to an office by Chriſt immediately, as the eleven were, and perſons called by him mediately by the Church, when one and the ſame end is deſigned them, which is the work of the Miniſtery, the perfecting the Saints, the edifying of the body of Chriſt, and to witneſs Chriſt his reſurrection? <hi>Acts</hi> 1.22. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13. I would be gladly informed (if any man could and would) whether there be any eſſential difference betwixt the twelve Apoſtles and the Apoſtles of the Churches, and wherein that difference doth conſiſt? If any man think it was becauſe the eleven were inſpired to be pen-men of Scripture, I anſwer, All of them were not, nor the Apoſtles onely. If any man think the doing of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: I anſwer, They alone did not do them, but many believers, alſo, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Matthias,</hi> though choſen mediately of the Church, had the ſame power in diſpenſations that the eleven had.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41271:32"/>3. If impoſition after Baptiſme were confined to Apoſtles onely that were immediately called, it would have been in vain, for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to have called it a foundation, and to have conjoyn'd it with ſuch neceſſary truths, as Faith and the Reſurrection was, ſeeing the perſons that had the power of adminiſtring them, were all in a ſhort time to be dead.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Every Church of Chriſt have the ſame power that the firſt Church had, both for Officers and Ordinances, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17, 18, 19. the firſt Church therefore having Officers to diſpenſe any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; as Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.26. Prophets, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.27, 32. Evangeliſts, as <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 6.5. other Churches may chuſe (having fitting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) the like Officers; and they being choſen, may execute acts that belong to the reſpective Offices: ſo that as the firſt Church continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Apoſtles doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. (of which laying on of hands was part, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.) did chuſe an Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.26. and the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> ſent out <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who before the ſending, ſeem to have been of the number of the Prophets, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. ſo may other Churches ſend out gratious and able men; neither let any man ſay, the Prophets at <hi>Antioch</hi> ſent out <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> for the whole Church faſted, and acted in the buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are this Church of Chriſt, and what is the eſſential note of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are a company of Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. into which ſocieties here on Earth though ſome Hypocrites creep, yet till God diſcover them they are looked upon as Saints; the Saintſhip of which company joyned together in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies reſpectively (leaving others to their light) I take to be the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial note of the Church, becauſe holineſs is the moſt ſpecial diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Church from the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat muſt a Chriſtian do, that he may receive worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preparedly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As he muſt examine himſelf, whether he be in Chriſt and the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41271:33"/> Spirit of God dwell in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Alſo it is very expedient (I will not ſay the not doing it is ſinful) that every time before a perſon receives, the ſaid perſon judge it ſelf before the Lord for what it hath done amiſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. but in any wiſe before thou comeſt, examine to finde good grounds of thy union with Chriſt, without which neither preſume to come to baptiſm nor the Supper, leſt they prove means of thy final hardneſs and impenitency.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was the end wherefore the Lords Supper was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. For the continual remembrance of Chriſt his death (which we deſire to ſhew forth to all men out of conſcience so his command, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25, 26.) and more particularly for the remembrance of the new Teſtament or Covenant which is eſtabliſhed in his death, wherein remiſſion of ſins is bequeathed to believers <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. Which I take (with ſubmiſſion to better judgement) to be the prime end, yea (as to me ſeemeth) the onely end of this inſtitution.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What mean you by calling the Lords Supper the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the blood of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. I mean, that whereas theſe was an old Covenant of works, which all men tranſgreſſing are condemned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.5. God was pleaſed to make a new Covenant with all the elect, to accept the ſacrifice of Chriſts death, as a ſatisfaction to his juſtice for our breaches of the firſt Covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14, 16, 18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. Which Covenant is not onely preſented to us by the Goſpel in audible words, but alſo viſibly to our ſenſe in the ſigns of the Covenant: ſo that as the Rainbow was a witneſs or ſign betwixt God and the Earth that he would no more drown it; and if he did, his bow ſhould witneſs againſt him: and as the blood of the paſſover ſprinkled upon the Iſraelites poſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 27.7. was a ſigne betiwxt God and the people, that God would ſpare them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. and if he did not, that blood ſhould witneſs againſt him: and as in covenants among men, they confirme them with ſome ſigns of memorial, that when they forget the bargain, it may be ſaid unto them. This is your hand or ſigne; ſo as in Baptiſme, ſo in the Lords Supper (for one and the ſame thing for number is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both) God for the ſtrengthning our belief appoints ſigns as
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41271:33"/> witneſſes againſt him if he go about to break his covenant, and as witneſſes againſt us if we forget our duty of faith, repentance, ſelf-denial, confeſſion of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein we have in thoſe ſignes by all deep engagement obliged our ſelves.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the danger of unworthy receiving?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In ſtead of receiving to comfort, Satan hath a greater poſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch perſons, as in <hi>Judas</hi> (if he were at the Supper, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned men think) who <hi>Luke</hi> 22.3. had Satan entring into him before his going to the High-Prieſts and receiving the ſop; but after the receiving the ſop, the Devil entred further into him, <hi>John</hi> 13.27, and <hi>v.</hi> 30. having received the ſop, he went out immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and came to a thorow reſolution to betray Chriſt; beſides, good men receiving in part unworthily, receive temporal judgements, as ſickneſs, weakneſs, death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. and wicked men having a total unworthineſs, receive eternal damnation.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the manner of Chriſt his preſence in the Lords Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is preſent ſpiritually to the Faith of the receiver, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by his Spirit the Union &amp; Communion of the ſoul with Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15, 16, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. he is alſo preſent by grace and operation of feeling, in the hearts of his, as the Sun is preſent with us, by his light and influence, though in Heaven: he is alſo preſent in the promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. Take, eat this is my body and my blood; as if he ſhould ſay, I promiſe you in the uſe of this Ordinance, you ſhall receive the vertue of my quickening death and merit thereof, as verily as you receive bread and wine.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What think you of that opinion, that the body of Chriſt is preſent, in, with, or, under the bread, after an unperceivable manner?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an erroneous opinion, It is againſt the Article of Chriſt his aſcenſion into heaven, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hereby they deſtroy the nature and truth of a humane body, which is both finite and viſible, making it infinite and inviſible.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Whether is the body of Chriſt really and ſubſtantially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under the kindes of bread and wine, in the ſame ſpace where bread and wine were contained before?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No: for 1. Bread in the Supper is ſix times after conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41271:34"/> called bread ſtill, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.15, 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The truth of Chriſts fleſh is proved by ſight and touching, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. but in the Supper it cannot he touched: therefore it is not ſubſtantially or fleſhlily preſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Its a contradiction, that one whole body ſhould be whole together in divers places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.6. he is riſen, he is not here: the conſequence had proved nothing, if a whole body might be whole in divers places.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How oft are we to receive the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Often: our own decayes of grace requires often receiving; the Apoſtles indeterminate Command, Do this as often, admits of no other limitation then want of occaſion and opportunity.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But there are ſome that are not in charity with me, may I receive?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, (ſuppoſing the uncharitableneſs on their parts) their ſin cannot debar us of the priviledges and benefits Chriſt hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for us; if the ſin be on our part, we muſt lay aſide our wrath, leſt we double our ſin by abſenting from Ordinances, and retaining wrath.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are the perſons to be received to the Supper?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Onely Church-Members. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. holy things are not to be given to Dogs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. in expoſing the ſigns of the Covenant to thoſe concerning whom we have no ground to believe God promiſes any thing, we prophane them; they are not to be acknowledged for Covenanters with God, who are his enemies.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How are wicked men partaking, guilty of the body and blood of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. They are guilty of rejecting it. 2. Becauſe they prophane the ſignes that repreſent Chriſts body; as they that deſpiſe Chriſts Servants, deſpiſe himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.8. or as a reproach done to the Ambaſſadors redounds to the Prince or as he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Treaſon againſt a Princes Seal, commits it againſt himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:41271:34"/>
               <head>Concerning Prayer.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A pouring forth of the Soul to God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 62.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are three:
<list>
                     <item>1. Confeſſion of ſins: ſo <hi>Daniel,</hi> c. 9.6, 7, 8, &amp;c. and <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> c. 1, 6.7.</item>
                     <item>2. Petition for grace, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9.</item>
                     <item>3. Thankſgiving for benefits, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What qualifications are requiſite, that we may pray com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. We being bankrupt in Heaven, muſt come in the name of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.23, 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For things according to Gods will, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. With a heart purpoſing againſt all ſin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9 41. <hi>Iob.</hi> 11.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. With a fervent heart, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.16. crying mightily to God, <hi>Jon.</hi> 3. as a Malefactor doth for life before a Judge.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In Faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.6, 7. believing we ſhall have from God ſo far as his promiſe reacheth; as a begger never goes from a door, ſo long as he believes he ſhall have an Almes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. &amp; 21.22. to perſons praying in faith, the thing deſired is done, or elſe its better for them not to be done.</p>
               <p n="6">6. With an humble and broken heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.17. content not your ſelves with prayers void of humiliation and melting of heart; ſo <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.27. the Prodigal, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.18. If Satan fright thee from prayer, becauſe thou art unworthy, ſay then, Nay, but I will pray, becauſe I am unworthy.</p>
               <p n="7">7. With watchfulneſs againſt diſtractions, both thoſe that come from Satan, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. and thoſe which come from ſpiritual fluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs eſpecially, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2. and watchfulneſs againſt drouzineſs, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.36. as a begger is all awake when he begs, ſo muſt we be when we beg of God.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41271:35"/>8. With ſighes and groanes, though words anſwer very barely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. God anſwers not that which is in the froth of wolds alone; but that which is in the ſigh or groan, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 145.19.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Pray with the Spirit, <hi>Jude</hi> 20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. which is not onely to have the gift of Prayer, (which artificial Chriſtians may have, and not without ſome ſhow of ſpiritual life, being full of fit expreſſions from abundance of notions) but alſo to have the grace of prayer, whereby the ſoul hath many ſighes againſt the ſproutings of luſts, and wraſtlings for the removals of corruptions; and ſecret ſpringings of heart upon the receipt of ſpiritual bleſſings, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1. that ſuch Prayers come from the Spirit, appears, becauſe when the Spirit intermits or forbears working, the ſouls of the beſt become dull, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Let thy Perſon be holy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. 2 <hi>John</hi> 15.7. no natural man can pray acceptably, <hi>John</hi> 9.13. yet may there be paſſions in a ſoul, and yet that ſoul holy, and that Prayer accepted, as in <hi>Elia's</hi> Caſe. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How ſhall a poor ſoul know whether God hears his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ſhall know it by theſe ſigns.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When he hath the thing granted, he prayed for; the Church prayed for <hi>Peter,</hi> and had him given when they were praying, <hi>Act.</hi> 12.5. <hi>Hanna</hi> prayed for a ſon, and had one, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.27. ſee for this, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.17. <hi>Jud.</hi> 13.8. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.9. &amp; 12. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.10. but becauſe temporal bleſſings may be ſevered from the good will of God, therefore we muſt judge of the anſwers of our Prayers, from the grants we have in ſpiritual bleſſings; as when we pray for a melting heart, or a thirſting heart, and have one given to us; and we may judge of temporal bleſſings to be the fruits of Prayers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, when thoſe bleſſings are uſed to a ſanctified end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By the enlargement of the heart to holy deſires, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. Thou haſt prepared their heart, thou wilt cauſe thine ear to hear; when a man hath a bag, and he falls to ſtretching of it, its a ſigne he means to fill it: ſo God enlarging the heart with more hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt, longings and breathings, then ordinary; Its a ſign he means to hear that prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When we behold the face of God in Prayer. God ſometimes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:41271:35"/> anſwers the Prayers of his People, with a caſt of his countenance; ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.7, 8, 9. alſo 22.24. as Petitioners may oft read their ſpeeding, in the amiable countenance of thoſe they petition. <hi>Job</hi> gaves an undeniable reaſon, why God was his ſalvation, <hi>Job.</hi> 13.16. which was, becauſe an hypocrite did not come before him as <hi>Job</hi> did: though every Creature come into his omnipreſence, yet into his ſpecial preſence, to behold his face in prayer, and to come within the liſt of his countenance, onely upright men come, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When the Conſcience is able to commend the Prayer, ſetting aſide the infirmities; <hi>Jobs</hi> Conſcience commended his Prayer to be pure, <hi>Job</hi> 16.17. If thy conſcience tell thee, thy Prayers are rotten, thy ſins not purged, thy heart not upright, it is the voice of God in thy ſoul; but if thy heart condemn thee not, then haſt thou confidence towards God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.21. onely note, ſometimes the Conſcience may be miſinformed under a temptation, to think God doth not hear them when he doth, <hi>Job</hi> 30.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1, 2. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.8. ſometimes they were perſwaded God heard their prayer, as <hi>verſe</hi> 46, 57. ſometimes they doubted thereof as <hi>verſe</hi> 44.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When though God denies us what we ask, yet God gives us a better thing; <hi>Abraham</hi> prayed that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> might live, and God gave him a better, even <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 17.18, 19. <hi>David</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the life of the Child he had by <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and God gave him a better, even <hi>Solomon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.22.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By Gods drawing neer unto us in our Prayer. God draws nigh to the Soul,</p>
               <p n="1">1. By removing diſcouragements, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.57. Thou draweſt neer in the day that I cryed unto thee; thou ſaidſt, Fear not. When God ſhall raiſe up the ſoul againſt diſcouragements from former ſcandalous ſins, from Gods juſtice, from its own unworthineſs, from dumbneſs and barrenneſs of expreſſions, from the ſinning againſt knowledge, from relapſes, from ſecret deſpair, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.22. this drawing nigh argues an anſwer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God draws nigh by working, meltings, and brokenneſs of heart upon the ſoul, ſo that as in old time, God was wont to give anſwer to the prayers of his Servants, by ſending fire from Heaven to conſume their Sacrifices, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.24. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.26.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41271:36"/> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.1. ſo doth he now teſtifie by his holy Spirit, who was typified by that fire, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. working in prayer many paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate meltings, that the heart melts under the diſpleaſing ſuch a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, and the eye melts into tears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.8. bleſſed be God who hath heard the <hi>voice of my weeping:</hi> how knew he he was heard? why, becauſe he poured out weeping prayers to God, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 39.12. hold not thy peace at my tears. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.5. I have heard thy prayers and ſeen thy tears. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9. I will lead them along with weeping and ſupplication. Alſo Chriſt when he was heard offered up ſtrong crying with tears, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.5. the like did <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> when he prayed that God would give him favour in the ſight of the King, he wept in his prayer, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.4, 11. alſo <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> wept and made ſupplication, and found the Lord in <hi>Bethel, Hoſ.</hi> 12.3, 4. yea the Saints of God generally have been thus crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with anſwers in their prayers, as <hi>Ezra,</hi> c. 10.1. <hi>Iob,</hi> c. 16, 16: <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.27. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20.31. <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.1. &amp; 13.17. <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Peter, Mar.</hi> 14.72. not as if God did not draw nigh in other prayers wherein the eye melts not into tears; for if the ſoul hath other ſigns of its prayers heard, it ought not to be diſcouraged; but this I ſay, prayers poured out thus with inward meltings of heart, ſo that the eye ſhall weep in prayer, ſeem to me to be crowningly anſwered. And ſo much the more, when a perſon is not inclining to weep in other Caſes, as many women, and ſome men are out of natural ſoftneſs. To conclude, conſider whether it be ſafe to be without ſuch a frame of heart and eye in prayer, as ſo many of the Saints in the word are recorded to have had, and wherein they found ſuch comfort and ſucceſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God draws nigh by chearing and inward comforting of the heart, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6, 7. inwardly warning it with the ſoul of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Now all theſe approaches of God to gracious ſouls are not alike; for ſometimes he gives a ſtronger ſenſe of his favour in one prayer more then another, and ſometimes in ſome one or more Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of the ſame prayer, then in other Petitions thereof; yet when God draws nigh to thy ſoul in a particular requeſt, it is not certain that that requeſt ſhall be granted in that manner you deſired, (as when a man prays for the life of a ſick friend, and God draws nigh in that Petition, and yet the friend dies) but it is evidential to thee, that thy prayer is heard, and that the thing thou askeſt is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:41271:36"/> to the approving will of God, though not according to his decreeing will.</p>
               <p>All theſe drawings nigh to the ſoul evidence the hearing of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as appears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.17. hear me ſpeedily; but what ſigne doth he deſire? why <hi>verſe</hi> 18. he ſaith, Draw nigh to my ſoul.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Thou mayeſt know thy prayers are anſwered, by having a ſpirit of perſeverance in prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.20. &amp; 138.3. when a Petitioner comes to a Prince or Nobleman, if the Prince embolden him in his ſpeech, and let him ſpeak all he would, its a ſign the Prince means to grant that man his Petition, becauſe otherwiſe he would not have endured to have heard him ſo long, but would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be gone: ſo when the ſoul comes to God in prayer, if God diſpatch it out of his preſence, that the ſoul hath no heart to continue its ſuit, and prayes deadly and dully, and is glad it hath ſaid its prayers and hath done; its a fearful ſign that God anſwers not thoſe prayers (though poured out by a godly man) but if thou prayeſt, and God gives thee a ſpirit to hold out in prayer; if thou prayeſt and haſt not done in thy prayers; but God doth further and further put in thee a warmth and heat of affection, that thy heart is emboldened in its Petitions, and thou deſireſt further Communion with God, that thou art as it were loath to leave off the words of prayer, much leſs the ſuits of prayer, it is a ſigne God will grant thy prayer to thee.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Thou mayeſt know thy prayers are heard, when in the cloſe of thy prayer thou haſt ſome comfortable anſwer ſuggeſted unto thee from God; for example, God by his Spirit comes to ſome, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting on this wiſe, when they pray powerfully, <hi>viz.</hi> I will be thy God, I will not fail thee nor forſake thee, I will do thee much good, I will be an everlaſting God unto thee; ſo God ſuggeſted to <hi>Paul</hi> at the end of his prayer, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. My grace is ſufficient for thee. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.5.7. when the Church was diſcouraged out of ſence of her unworthineſs, God drew neer and ſaid, Fear not: ſo <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> c. 44. ſaith, O that I could call upon God with the ſame fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, as oft as I would; for when I pray in this manner, (meaning fervently) this anſwer ſeems ſenſibly to be given unto me, <hi>Fiat quod petis,</hi> let the thing be done which thou deſireſt. No man (ſaith he) can contemn this prayer which proceeds from inward bowels and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41271:37"/> affection; much leſs can it be in vain with God; for this laſt ſigne, I am confident ſome of Gods Children have it; but whether all have it, I leave it to further enquiry.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The manner of the falling out of things evidenceth prayer-hearing, when God brings a thing to paſs through many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, contriving all the paſſages in a buſineſs, whereof if any of them had been wanting, the buſineſs had not been effected; ſo when the Church was delivered in anſwer to the Prayers of <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai;</hi> ſo when <hi>Peter</hi> was brought out of priſon, beyond expectation, it plainly appears it was the fruit of prayer: when God makes the way eaſie and plain after prayer, and the courſe of things begins to change, and we meet with comforts in ſtead of former croſſes, it appears it is from prayers anſwered, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 12.12, 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Gods with-drawments from the Soul.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHether may not God with-draw from his own Children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes: if God forſake Chriſt his onely begotten Son, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.38. in reſpect of comfort and joy, though not in reſpect of union of natures, then Believers muſt not look to go free.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Why doth God with-draw from his children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Careleſs and negligent uſe of means of grace, or an overly performance of duties of Religion, <hi>Song</hi> 5.2, 2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For grieving his Spirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.10. either by ſcandalous ſins, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.11. or treacherous denial of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. Chriſt will deny to ſuch, comfort as well as owning.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not eſteeming Gods preſence, <hi>Iob</hi> 15.11. we prize things in their abſence.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To make us grow in a hatred of ſin, as of that which deprives us of Communion with God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.17.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That we may know what Chriſt underwent for us, in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Gods preſence, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41271:37"/>6. To try whether we will truſt in God in the want of feeling, <hi>Job</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What may comfort a ſoul, when God withdraws comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able feeling and influence of his preſence, which the ſoul hath formerly felt in Prayer and other Ordinances?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are divers comforts, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Thy ſadneſs for his abſence doth argue a former enjoyment of his preſence; and being once Chriſts, thou art ever Chriſts, <hi>John</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A man may fear God and have part in Chriſt, and yet feel little or no comfort, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As in the gloomieſt day there is ſo much light, whereby we may know it to be day, and not night, ſo a Chriſtian whom God hath in part forſaken, may diſcern himſelf to be ſincere, becauſe he hath a love to God and his glory, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.18. vehement deſires after grace and Gods preſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. and an abſolute pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt ſin, though he ſhould dye without comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17, 18.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, a Chriſtian in a forſaken Eſtate, breathing out ſighs and groans for the return of <hi>Chriſts</hi> preſence, may be as dear to God, as he that enjoyes Gods preſence, <hi>Job</hi> 13.15.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Abſence of accuſtomed feelings then onely argue a back-ſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart, when they are ſuffered in the ſoul without ſorrow and grief, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28.1. &amp; 143.7. yet are not thy groans and ſorrows the cauſes of Gods return, but the diſpoſitions of perſons to whom he doth return.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Chriſt in his withdrawment, as well as in his return, aimes at his ſouls good; for upon his withdrawment, the ſoul is ſtretched with deſire after him <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1.</p>
               <p n="7">7. God withdraws from the ſpirits of Saints, onely in crowning graces; as joy, peace, feeling: not in ſaving graces; as faith, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſelf-denial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe God never takes away.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But why do you ſay, Faith, repentance, ſelf-denial,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are never taken away? are they not Creatures, and every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſubject to periſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Grace of it ſelf conſidered, may dye, for it is a Creature; but conſider it as united to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo it cannot dye, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. If believers were cut off from Chriſt, grace ſhould wither, as the branch being
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41271:38"/> cut off from the root doth; but being knit to him, the ſap muſt be in the branches, becauſe it is in the root; and life will be in the members, becauſe it is in the head: waters will never dry up, ſo long as there is a Fountain to maintain them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may I recover the feeling of the Lords love to my ſoul?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Cry mightily for his preſence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6 7. &amp; 27.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Enquire when, where, and why God with-drew, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.8. as we do concerning dear friends when they abſent themſelves from us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Converſe in all Ordinances wherein there is any in-comes of God. Some receive comfort in reading, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.11, 19. others in Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.39. others in hearing, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. others in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Be humble and afflicted under Gods withdrawment, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.53. vallies are bleſt with the happieſt influence of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Call to remembrance thy former times of comfort, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.5, 6. aſſuring thy ſelf thou haſt to deal with an unchangeable God. Though in winter the ſap in plants goes into the root, yet will it at <hi>Spring</hi> ſpread it ſelf in the branches.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Count no condition in the world too much, though it were baniſhment, impriſonment, reproach, or poverty, ſo thou maiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Gods countenance. Many are ſo dainty, that they will not ſuffer any thing for God, and therefore God inflicts that which is the greateſt of ſufferings, that is, the with-drawment of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Beware of reſting contented in the comfort of any Creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e without God and his ſweet preſence: the whole earth is a barren Wilderneſs without himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Give not way to ſpiritual drouzineſs.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But my heart is drouzy, how ſhall I keep it awake?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Uſe wakeful conſiderations, as of the ſhortneſs of life, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of glory, the danger of back-ſliding, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Keep your ſelves in the light: darkneſs makes men fit to ſleep.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nouriſh Gods fear, which is a wakeful affection, as being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant about danger. Fear of God, and comfort of the Holy Ghoſt, go together, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:41271:38"/>4. Keep company with wakeful Chriſtians, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Conſider the danger of a drouzy Eſtate. As firſt, Its trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the conſcience, <hi>Song</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. Secondly, Its the fore-runner of ſome great croſs or ſin, <hi>Song</hi> 5.2. &amp; 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Tentations.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is a Tentation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As it is an act in the Creature, it is the moving of a man to ſome ſin, with ſome reaſon to inforce it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.18, 19. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.11, 12.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are the tempters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. The Devil, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. 2. The World, by which I mean the wicked of the World, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10. and the goods therein. 3. The fleſh within us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What remedy againſt Satans tentations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Diſpute not with them things. <hi>Eve</hi> was foil'd, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1. He hath many methods which we cannot fathom.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Get faith to quench his fiery darts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. which is to be ſet a work in believing that Satan was ſpoiled and ſtript of his power over thy ſoul by Chriſt on the Croſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Uſe the Ordinance of prayer, for ſtrength to reſiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. and wiſdom to diſcern his tentations, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5. and long-ſuffering, that he may not tire us with the length of them. 2. Of the Word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. both in the Command, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.13, and in the promiſe, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. ſet this againſt all his proffers; and in the threathing: God telling <hi>Eve,</hi> if ſhe eat of the tree ſhe ſhould die, and ſhe liſtening to Satan, minced of the matter to this, Leſt ye dye, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3. and ſo was overcome by Satan.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Avoid three-things, 1. Idleneſs. When perſons are idle, Satan hath an opportunity to tempt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2. 2. Solitarineſs, this breeds melancholy, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.9, 10. 3. Secreſie, this makes the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41271:39"/> wound of an afflicted Conſcience bleed inwardly, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16. But if thou canſt have eaſe from God, let no man know the matter; but if not open thy Conſcience to ſome grave and godly friend, and herein be ſure to diſcover that evil that turns the Conſcience out of its place.</p>
               <p n="5">5. O draw good out of Satans tentations, and ſo he will have no courage to tempt; as more ſtrongly to believe there is a God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Satan tempts us to doubt whether there be a God; ſo the more to aſſure our ſelves we are Gods people, becauſe he ſo tempts us now, being he little tempted us when we were in our natural ſtate; in a word, learn by tentations, how to comfort tempted perſons.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What muſt I do when Satans temptation is paſt and gone?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As Mariners make their tacklings in a calme, firm againſt a ſtorme come: ſo when temptations are over, prepare for new a en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, remembring Satan leaves us only for a ſeaſon, <hi>Luk</hi> 4.13. though Chriſt overcame Satan, yet he came again and again. Satan will try whether we have loſt our former ſtrength, care, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; or whether God that would not ſuffer him then, will, for ſome ſins we have committed ſince, ſuffer him to have power over us now: Satan ſometimes politickly gives way for a ſeaſon, when yet his temptation is not overcome.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What remedy againſt the temptations of the world?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> If you mean by the World, the wicked of the Word; then conſent not to them: be you as importunate in reſiſting, as they ſhall be in tempting <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.10. But if you mean by World, the pleaſures, profits, and honours of the World; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider their uncertainty, their tranſitorineſs, their inability to fill the ſoul, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.16. Let us love them onely in reference to God and a good Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What remedy againſt the temptations of the fleſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Take heed of ſpiritual pride; God ſuffers ſuch to fall, as appears in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Look not diſdainfully upon any ſin in others, ſeeing thy nature is not free from the ſame, at leaſt in the ſeed of it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. God gives many men over to vile temptations, to cure their pride.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Watchfulneſs, <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>ult. Prov.</hi> 4.23.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Keep your ſelves from ſinful occaſions, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10. If thou
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41271:39"/> wilt not keep thy ſelf from occaſions, God will not keep thee from the ſin; yea, if thou venture on occaſions, thou haſt a ſecret liking of ſin, whatſoever thy pretences be.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Set againſt the motions that come from the fleſh before Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ſuggeſtions meet with them; when both forces are joyned, they are ſo much ſtronger.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Reſiſt the cauſing ſin, and ſo the effect will ceaſe: to cure paſſion, reſiſt pride.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is one ſin the cauſe of another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By effecting or making it: ſo covetouſneſs brings forth theft, as in <hi>Achan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By deſerving it, when we deſerve to be caſt into ſome ſin by God; not that God doth infuſe the matter or form of a puniſhing ſin: but by letting luſt out, and ſetting Satan looſe upon us, we are corrected by one ſin for another, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24, 26, 28. When a ſin deſerves to have another ſin made the puniſhment of it, we muſt make our peace for the cauſing ſin, before the effect will ceaſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.12, 13. This forſaking, ſuffering, and delivering up the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is an act of juſtice in God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What other remedies againſt fleſhly temptations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Apply the threatnings and Commandments againſt it, and the promiſes in caſe we do reſiſt and overcome, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be earneſt with God, to mortifie it by his Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</p>
               <p>Make no proviſions for thy fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Croſs thy fleſh, by endeavouring to do clean contrary to what it ſuggeſts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Reſiſt the beginning of fleſhly ſuggeſtions, <hi>Jud.</hi> 23. <hi>Cain</hi> not repenting of envy, it came to murther. <hi>Judas</hi> not repenting of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, it came to murther: if a Serpent get in its head, it will ſoon get in its body.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Venture not upon any ſin, becauſe Satan tells you it is ſmall, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. By liſtning to this ſuggeſtion, many exceedingly harden their hearts.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>When are temptations of luſts ſufficiently reſiſted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. 1. When we hate them, pray, ſigh, and groan againſt them; but ſin reigns where it is loved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:41271:40"/>2. When we do not practiſe at all groſs and preſumptuous evils for which God threatens out of heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10 11. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.3, 4. and when we weaken leſs evils; which appears we do, when the judgement commands the will, the will the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and the affections the actions.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How may we know when temptations come from Satan, when from our luſts?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is very hard, if poſſible to know, where the point of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is; if we reject them, whether they come from Satan or us, they ſhall not be imputed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20, 21. Come the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation which way it will, no more is imputed by God then is ſeen and allowed.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What remedy againſt unholy thoughts whether they come from Satan or corruption?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Complain of them to Chriſt, who had ſuch inſpired and caſt into his mind by <hi>Satan,</hi> though not ariſing from himſelf; pray as <hi>David Pſal.</hi> 19.12, 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Waſh thy heart in Chriſt his blood, that it may be enabled to think good thoughts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Study good thoughts. Carnal men have many good thoughts caſt into their hearts, which they caſt out again as faſt; but their hearts have no good thoughts ariſing from them: contrarily Gods people, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.23. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What means are there to govern our tongues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Pray to God to ſet a watch over them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Get an holy frame of heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.34, 35. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.30, 31. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.23. A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart, bringeth forth good things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let the purpoſe of thy heart be ſet againſt unholy ſpeaking, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Suppreſs ſin when it is onely in the motion, ſo will it not come forth of the tongue, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be ſparing in thy words: men that ſpeak much, muſt needs laſh out, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.3, 7. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.27.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Firſt think, then ſpeak, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.23.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſad account that men who ſpeak idle words muſt give, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. <hi>Jude</hi> 1 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20, 21.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:41271:40"/>8. Conſider, a happy life depends much on the well-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the tongue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.12. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.33. And upon the miſ-government of it, comes much of our miſery, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10.13, 14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.6.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Inure your ſelves to gracious and ſavory words, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. powdered with ſalt; ſo that as ſalt draws out of meat putrifying humors, and makes it relliſhable for the palate, and fit for dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: ſo ſhould a principle of grace in the heart purge rottenneſs out of the tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Family-Duties.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHat is the duty of a Maſter of a Family?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To provide for their ſouls, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and bodies of his Family, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Husbands Duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To love his wife as himſelf, affording comforts to her as to himſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.28. and not to be bitter to her, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Wives Duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Submiſſion to their Husbands, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18. and reverence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, inward in heart, and outward in carriage, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.33.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the Parents Duties towards their Children?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To train them up in Gods wayes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.4. and to provide for them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the childs duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To honour their Parents, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.2. and to obey them in all lawful things, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.20. and to requite their kindneſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Maſters duty to his Servant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To give them what is juſt and equal, knowing they have a Maſter in heaven, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the Servants duty?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To honour their Maſters, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. and ſincerely to do
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41271:41"/> them ſervice, abhorring eye-ſervice, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22. doing ſervice not onely for the gaine of their wages, but principally out of Conſcience to the Lord, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.5, 6, 7. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.23, 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Reſurrection and last Judgement.</head>
               <p>Q. <hi>WHether ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re be a Reſurrection of the Body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Yes, <hi>John</hi> 5.28. All that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, ſome to the Reſurrection of life, and ſome to the Reſurrection of eternal damnation, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What Body ſhall riſe again? the ſame, or another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The ſame body in number, though with more glorious qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; as the ſame ſeed that is ſown groweth again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.36. So that the godly when they riſe again ſhall ſee God, not with other, but with theſe ſame eyes, <hi>Job</hi> 19.25, 26, 27. He means the eyes of his body, becauſe he ſaith, I, and I my ſelf, and not a ſtranger; and becauſe he mentions his skin, fleſh, and the ſame eyes he then had: It is juſt, that <hi>Jobs</hi> eyes that had wept tears, and <hi>Pauls</hi> body that bore brands or markes of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.17. ſhould be rewarded, and not a new made body or new eyes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42. The Apoſtle pointing at his own body, ſaith, This corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall put on incorruption, and this mortal ſhall put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, <hi>John</hi> 2.19. Deſtroy this Temple, and I will raiſe it up; meaning the Temple of his body. See alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. <hi>John</hi> 11.24.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth it appear that the bodies of Saints ſhall riſe the ſame bodies, but with new qualities?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Apoſtle makes it appear by a plain ſimilitude, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.35, 37. of a wheat-corn caſt into the earth, which being rotten comes forth, not naked hard, dry, &amp; without life, as it was ſown; nor rotten, as it was in the earth; but keeping the ſame ſubſtance and kind, it comes forth with new qualities of ears, husk &amp; ſtalk, being living and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41271:41"/> full of juice; ſo the ſame body in number ſhall riſe again, but with more glorious qualities.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are thoſe glorious qualities our bodies ſhall riſe with?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. They are theſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Incorruptibility, they ſhall not dye any more, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Gloriouſneſs, they ſhall ſhine like the glorious body of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Powerfulneſs, it ſhall be raiſed in power, able to move whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.43. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16.17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Spirituality 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. not onely becauſe it ſhall not need meat, drink, or apparel; but alſo becauſe it ſhall be like a ſpirit in the nimbleneſs of its motion, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What follows the reſurrection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. The laſt and general Judgement, <hi>John</hi> 6.39. I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who ſhall be judged?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. All perſons ſhall come to judgement: the godly having their ſins forgiven them, ſhall come to a judgement of tryal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.38. but the wicked unto a judgement of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.28.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who ſhall be the Judge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Although the Trinity ſhall judge, yet the Exerciſe and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of it is committed to the Son, <hi>John</hi> 5.22, 27. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42. &amp; 17.31. He is moſt fit to be Judge; for as God he knows the ſecrets of all hearts, and he is fit to ſpeak to man, as being man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the rules Chriſt will proceed by in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Such as never had the Scriptures, ſhall be judged by the Law writ in their hearts, they not having walked ſutably thereto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. and thoſe that have had onely the old Teſtament, ſhall be judged out of that, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.45. and thoſe that have had the whole word, ſhall be judged out of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What will Ieſus Chriſt do after he is ſet in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. All ſhall be called forth, and the ſheep evidencing their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41271:42"/> faith in Chriſt, not onely by their words. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.38. but alſo by their works, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. ſhall receive the bleſſed ſentence of abſolution: <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you;</hi> but the Goats having neither faith nor fruits, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.42, 43. ſhall be ſo ſtraitly reckoned with, that they ſhall be called to an account for every ungodly ſpeech. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.37. <hi>Jude</hi> 15. and ſo ſhall receive that dreadfull ſentence, <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But ſeeing there are ſome wretched men that deny the Scriptures, how ſhall I know the Scriptures to be Gods Word?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There are many grounds to ſway the Conſcience to belief of them, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Witneſs of Gods Spirit which is promiſed to be given to all the Elect, together with the word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As natural bodies declare what they are; as Sun, Moon, Stars, Fire, Water, Gold, Silver, Hony; ſo doth the word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7, 8, 9, no book, but breaths out holineſs to the Lord, no Chapter hardly, but takes off our hearts from the World; it ſets forth his infinite mercy to his Saints, and infinite juſtice to the wicked. The Scripture is like the light which not onely ſhews other things, but it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The agreement of the Scriptures one part with another, though the writers lived remote one from another, and in ſeveral ages of the World. How could they have ſo agreed, were they not written by one Spirit? Seeing two Hiſtorians, if they write of any time or occurrence, through ignorance, partiality, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, they will contradict each other, if they be onely humane writers; beſides, for the old Teſtament we have the Jews, the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt enemies of Chriſtianity, witneſſing it; and, and for the new, it doth harmoniouſly agree with the old.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The impartiality of the pen-men; they ſpeak impartially to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41271:42"/> all, to Princes as well as beggers. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of his own mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.14. <hi>Moſes</hi> tells of the faults of his own Granfather <hi>Levi, Gen.</hi> 49.5, 7. whereas men naturally raiſe up their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors to the higheſt. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets forth his blaſphemy and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By the end at which they aime: had theſe Pen-men wrote as men, they would have lifted up themſelves; but every book throws down man as low as hell, and exalts God with the higheſt excellence, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.15, 16. and gives the glory of all to God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By the ſubject matter of the Scriptures. Hardly any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of men, but ſome luſts are ſcattered up and down, of pride, vain-glory: But in the Scriptures every word is pure, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.5. more then ſilver ſeven times purified, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 12.6, 7. had men writ it, they would never have tyed themſelves to ſuch ſtrict points.</p>
               <p n="7">7. There are many things in the Scripture that could never have proceeded from the brain of man; for example, that in one eſſence or being, the Father, Son, and Spirit ſhould ſubſiſt, that our bodies turned to duſt ſhould riſe again the in ſame number, though with more glorious qualities; ſo the incarnation of Chriſt by a Virgin, for the appeaſing the juſtice of God. So, that all things which befall a Chriſtian ſhall work together for his good, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Salvation. If theſe and many other things could not enter into his brain, much leſs could they proceed from his pen.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The powerful effects the Scriptures have upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, prove them to be of God; for example, they melt the heart in in reading them, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.19. they ſtrike a terrour into the hearts of the ungodly. No writings of men can ſo awe the hearts of men, as theſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11. they over-power the will. One verſe of ſelf-denial will make a man part with all his Eſtate, Friends, and Life, and what not? they work a wonderful change in many perſons, that they are not the ſame they were; yea, they quicken
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41271:43"/> dead hearts, and revive the dejected, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119.49, 50. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The books themſelves bear witneſs, they are from God. In moſt books of Scriptures, in the entrance of them, the names of the pen-men, together with the Author of the word, are expreſſed: See <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Ioel</hi> 1.1. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, its poſſible for falſe writings to have ſuch Titles prefixt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> True, the name is not enough, were there nothing elſe; but this being joyned with other ſigns, is of great force. Shall we believe <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> or <hi>Plato</hi>'s works to be their works, when they have their names affixt thereto, and ſhall we not believe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to be of them whoſe Title they bear, that is the word of God by ſuch and ſuch a writer?</p>
               <p n="10">10. The death and ſufferings of the Martyrs who have given their lives to ſeal the truth, proves them to be of God, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9. &amp; 20.4. Where do we ever find any to dye, to defend the opinions of <hi>Plato,</hi> or the dreams of <hi>Mahomet?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Satans</hi> malice proves it; he never tempts us to unbeliefe of any writings, ſave theſe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The fulfilling of the Prophecies proves them to be of God, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 44.28. named <hi>Cyrus</hi> to be the deliverer of Gods people an hundred and ſixty yeers before <hi>Cyrus</hi> was born. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> ſet the bounds of ſeventy yeers to the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity. <hi>Daniel</hi> lived onely in the two firſt Monarchies, the <hi>Caldean</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> yet he propheſies of the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchies. So, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be in <hi>Egypt</hi> four hundred yeers, and then come out; ſo that he that ſhould build <hi>Jericho,</hi> ſhould lay the foundation of it in his eldeſt ſon, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 6.26. compared with 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 16.34. <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied of Doctrines forbidding Marriage and meates, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And now its come to paſs in the Papacy. <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 49. ſpeaks of all the portions his Children ſhould have, aſſigning to one the Corn-Countrey, to others the Sea, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41271:43"/> the vine-grounds, as they were after divided by lot certain hundred yeers after: how could he come to the knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but by him that over-rules all lots? ſure they could not be ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by any but God, who knew what he would do. The ſeeing ſo many of the Prophecies to be fulfilled, may aſſure us alſo, that the reſt ſhall be fulfilled, and conſequently that they are all of God.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Either the Scriptures muſt be of God, or of man: not of man, becauſe then they muſt be either of bad men or of good; not of bad men, for they would never have forbid evil ſo rigorouſly, nor command good ſo expreſly, nor aimed ſo at Gods glory; nor of good men, for they durſt not have belied God, nor take the glory ſo due to God (which is to rule in the Conſcience) unto themſelves: therefore muſt they needs be of God.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The wonderful preſervation of the Scriptures, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Tyrants endeavour to aboliſh it, and Hereticks endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to corrupt it, yet it hath been kept pure in both the Originals: the two Tables writ by Gods own finger, were laid up in the Arke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.2. When <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> that they might the better draw the people to Idolatry, had ſuppreſt the book of the Law; it pleaſed God in rhe dayes of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> that it was found in the ruines of the Temple, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.14. <hi>Antiochus,</hi> 1 <hi>Mach.</hi> 1.56, 57. rent the book of the Law in peeces, and burnt it in the fire, and made it matter of death for a man to have a Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by him. <hi>Diocleſian</hi> the perſecuting Emperor forbad the uſe of the Scriptures, and burnt them; yet were the Scriptures ſtill preſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If An Argument from man were any thing material, I might adde, that the</hi> Iewiſh <hi>Bible, who are the uttereſt enemies of Chriſtianity, their old Teſtament agrees with ours, and for the truth of the</hi> Iewiſh <hi>Bible, they have teſtimony from the</hi> Samaritans, <hi>who were enemies to them, and an irreconciliable rent made betwixt them; yet in the</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:41271:44"/> Samaritan <hi>Bible (as ſome of the learned affirme) there is no difference at all to any purpoſe. Alſo the conſent of the godly Fathers and Chriſtians from Christ his time, who have from hand to hand delivered them to us, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned them with their commentaries, whoſe commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we have to ſhew in every age, well-nigh from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, ſome of whom confirmed the truth with their Lives and Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:41271:44"/>
            <head>A ſhort Catechiſme FOR BABES.</head>
            <p>Q. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow doth it appear that there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the creati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of heaven and earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 4.23. immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. infinite, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.27. knowing all things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. and preſent everywhere, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 139.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth this God ſubſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In the being of Father, Son, and Spirit; who are all one God, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whether is the Father Son or Spirit greateſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is an equality of glory, eternity, and power, in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41271:45"/> Father, Son, and Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did God make man at firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Pure and holy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. but we all fell in our firſt parents, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What befell unto us by</hi> Adams <hi>fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The judgement came upon all, to condemnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15, 16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the condition of every man ſince the fall of</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>A. Dead in treſpaſſes and ſins and by nature children of wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1, 3.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What way is there to come out of this miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Onely by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we to conſider eſpecially in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 1. His natures. 2. His offices.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the natures of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They are two:
<list>
                  <item>1. His Godhead.</item>
                  <item>2. His Manhood.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was it needful that he ſhould be God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That he might make the ſufferings of his Manhood of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite worth and vertue, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was it needful that he ſhould be man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That he might dye and ſatisfie Gods juſtice in the ſame nature that had offended, <hi>Matthew</hi> 20.28. 1 <hi>Corinthians</hi> 15.21, 22.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the offices of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They are three.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. His Kingly, Prieſtly, and Prophetical office.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Why was Chriſt a King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That he may reign in the hearts of his people, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.27. and in the Churches, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was he a Prophet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To reveale his Fathers will; ſo that are to hear him in all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:41271:45"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was he a Prieſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To offer ſacrifice for the ſins of his people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſacrifice did Chriſt offer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> His own body on the croſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.25, 26. wherewith he appears in Gods preſence for his people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. his blood ſpeaking good things.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A taking of Chriſt as a Lord and a Saviour, and reſting upon his ſatisfaction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.7.8.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What accompanies Juſtifying faith, without which it is not in the ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An holy diſpoſition or intention of heart to confeſs the truth of God, though with the loſs of all we have in the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A thorow change of the purpoſes of the heart, whereby they are univerſally ſet againſt all ſin, with an hatred of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.22.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meaſure of love muſt we love the Lord with?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> With a ſovergaine love; better then father or mother, ſon or daughter, yea then our own lives, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37, 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What denial of Chriſt is that which ſhuts perſons out of heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Habitual denial, or denial of Chriſt in the purporſe of our hearts; when we, for the ſaving of our lands, liberties, country, or lives, will deny Chriſt, or any part of his truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.33. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture reveal concerning ſpiritual Life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That whereas we are all dead men by <hi>Adams</hi> ſin and our own, when God pardons we are alive, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other life hath believers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A life of holineſs, whereby believing ſouls are quickned up to all the wayes of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ought to be the ground of a Chriſtian mans obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The command of Chriſt, which is the bond of the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.22.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:41271:46"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What other ground is there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The love of God, from whence our obedience ought to flow, <hi>John</hi> 14.15. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth the Scripture reveal of the combat of fleſh and Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The fleſh luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the fleſh; ſo that we cannot do the good we would do, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What may comfort in this combat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we hate the evil that we do, and love the good we do, and hunger and third to do the good we do not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the danger of ſinning againſt conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Such ſhall be puniſhed with many ſtripes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to live by faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To reſt on Gods promiſe for every good thing, without uſing unlawful means, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11, 12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the new Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is Gods work, whereby he not onely pardons all the ſins of all the Elect, and gives them eternal life through the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, but alſo promiſeth to take away their ſtony hearts, and writes his laws in their hearts, and cauſes them to relliſh and ſavour good things, and vouchſafes to be their God, and takes them to be his people. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Pouring out of the ſoul before God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.2.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the parts of prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are ſometimes divided in four parts, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. yet may we reduce them to three parts: firſt, confeſſion of ſins. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, petition for grace and favors. Thirdly, thankſgiving for benefits. To which we may add interceſſions to turn away judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What principal Properties ought there to be in an holy prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ought to be offered from a believing ſoul, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. in the name of Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23, 24. from the Spirit aſſiſting with ſighs and groans, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. for things according to the will of God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:41271:46"/>
            <p>A. It is a ſign of a believers fellowſhip with Chriſt in his death, burial, and reſurrection; that as his body is buried in water, ſo his ſins are buried through the ſatisfaction of Chriſt; and as he riſeth out of the water, ſo he is bound to walk with Chriſt in newneſs of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4 5, 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are the perſons to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe who are made Diſciples, and make profeſſion of their faith and repentance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15, 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.37, 38.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the end why the Lords Supper was appointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. For the continual remembrance of the ſacrifice of Chriſts death, and remiſſion of ſins which believers have therein, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25.26.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt a Chriſtian do, that he may receive worthily or preparedly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He muſt examine himſelf, whether he be in Chriſt, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spirit of God dwell in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the danger of unworthy receiving?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Temporal judgement, if they repent; eternal, if they repent not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore are hands laid upon believers after baptiſm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That they may receive a further increaſe of the Spirit therein, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is revealed concerning the reſurrection of the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That all ſhall riſe againe: the godly to the reſurrection of eternal life, the wicked to the reſurrection of eternal damnation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.28.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>With what bodies ſhall the Saints ariſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. with the ſame body in number, but with more glorious qualities, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43, 44, 53. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat follows the reſurrection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The laſt judgement, wherein all ſhall be judged of every thing done in the body, whether it be good or evil, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.40. <hi>John</hi> 5.28. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.12, 13, 14.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
